<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-12T04:38:43+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">And Other Withered Stumps Of Time</title><subtitle>A math blog.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Taut foliations and minimal surfaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/18/taut-foliations-minimal-surfaces/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taut foliations and minimal surfaces" /><published>2024-03-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/18/taut-foliations-minimal-surfaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/18/taut-foliations-minimal-surfaces/"><![CDATA[<p>The goal of this post is to prove the following theorem of Hansklaus Rummler and Dennis Sullivan. The references I used are “Foliations and the Geometry of 3-Manifolds” by Danny Calegari and “Combinatorial volume preserving flows and taut foliations” by David Gabai.</p>

<p><b>Theorem</b>. Let \(\mathcal{F}\) be a co-orientable codimension one foliation of an oriented closed smooth \(n\)-manifold \(M\). Then the following are equivalent:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>\(\mathcal{F}\) is taut,</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There is a positive volume form on \(M\) and a volume-preserving flow on \(M\) transverse to \(\mathcal{F}\),</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There is a Riemannian metric on \(M\) such that the leaves are locally area-minimizing.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Suppose \(\mathcal{F}\) is taut. Then for any \(p \in M\), we can find an embedded loop \(\phi : S^1 \to M\) transverse to \(\mathcal{F}\) passing through \(p\). Take a slight thickening to \(\phi : S^1 \times D^{n-1} \to M\). We arrange \(\phi\) by a small homotopy so that \(\phi^{-1}(\mathcal{F})\) is the natural product foliation on \(S^1 \times D^{n-1}\) by \(\{pt\} \times D^{n-1}\). Since \(M\) is compact, we may cover it by finitely many such embedded tori \(\phi_i : S^1 \times D^{n-1} \to M\). Let \(\theta_i\) denote a \((n-1)\)-form on \(S^1 \times D^{n-1}\) which on the leaves \(\{pt\} \times D^{n-1}\) restrict to a positive volume form on the interior of the disk and vanishes near the boundary \(\{pt\} \times \partial D^{n-1}\). Define:</p>

\[\displaystyle \theta_{\mathcal{F}} = \sum_i (\phi_i)_* \theta_i\]

<p>By construction, \(\theta_{\mathcal{F}}\) is a leafwise positive volume form on \(M\). Let \(\alpha\) be the \(1\)-form on \(M\) such that \(\ker \alpha = T\mathcal{F}\) is the distribution given by tangent spaces to the leaves of the foliation. Define \(\omega = \alpha \wedge \theta_{\mathcal{F}}\). Let \(X\) be the unique vector field such that \(\theta_{\mathcal{F}}(X) = 0\) and \(\alpha(X) = 1\). Then,</p>

\[\mathcal{L}_X \omega = i_X d\omega + di_X \omega = d i_X \omega = d\theta_{\mathcal{F}} = 0\]

<p>Therefore, \(X\) is a volume-preserving flow transverse to \(\mathcal{F}\). This proves (1) implies (2).</p>

<p>Suppose we have a positive volume form \(\omega\) on \(M\) and a volume-preserving flow \(X\) transverse to \(\mathcal{F}\). Let \(\theta = i_X \omega\), which must be a positive volume form on the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\). Let \(K = \ker(\theta)\), so that we have \(TM = T\mathcal{F} \oplus K\). Define a Riemannian metric on \(M\) by \(g = g_l \oplus g_k\) where \(g_l\) is a metric on the distribution \(T\mathcal{F}\) so that \(\theta\) is the Riemannian volume form on the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\) with respect to \(g_l\), and \(g_k\) is a positive definite metric on \(K\).</p>

<p>The important property that \(\theta\) has is as follows. Clearly, for any orthonormal \((n-1)\)-frame in \(T \mathcal{F}\), \(\theta\) evaluates to \(1\) on it. For an orthonormal \((n-1)\)-frame in \(TM\), \(\theta\) completely ignores the components of all the vectors in the direction of \(K\). Therefore, it evaluates to at most \(1\) on such a frame, with equality only if the frame is tangential to the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\). One says \(\theta\) is a calibration for the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\). Let \(L\) be a leaf of \(\mathcal{F}\). For any compact codimension zero submanifold-with-boundary \((\Omega, \partial \Omega) \subset L\) and a perturbed copy of it \(\Omega' \subset M\) with \(\partial \Omega = \partial \Omega'\) representing \([\Omega] \subset H_2(M, \partial \Omega; \Bbb R)\), we must have the following:</p>

\[\displaystyle \mathrm{vol}_g(\Omega) = \int_{\Omega} \theta = \int_{\Omega'} \theta \leq \int_{\Omega'} \mathrm{vol}_g = \mathrm{vol}_g(\Omega')\]

<p>where the inequality above is true by the calibration property. Consequently, the leaves of \(L\) are locally area-minimizing with respect to the metric \(g\), i.e., they are minimal hypersurfaces. This proves (2) implies (3).</p>

<p>It remains to prove (3) implies (1). Given a Riemannian metric \(g\) such that each leaf of \(\mathcal{F}\) is locally area-minimizing, we may consider an \((n-1)\)-form \(\theta\) which restricts to the Riemannian volume form on each leaf. This is a calibration for all the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\), as above. Suppose \(\mathcal{F}\) is not taut. Fix a transverse co-orientation of \(\mathcal{F}\). Let \(L \subset M\) be a leaf of \(\mathcal{F}\). Define the accessible set \(A(L)\) to be the set of points \(x \in M\) such that there is a positively directed arc transverse to \(\mathcal{F}\) from \(L\) to \(x\). Clearly, \(A(L)\) is open and  saturated by leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\), therefore the boundary \(\partial A(L)\) is also a (possibly empty) union of leaves. However, if \(A(L) = M\), then every leaf admits a positive transversal arc from \(L\) from both negative and positive sides, which we can combine to produce a transverse circle through every leaf, contradicting our hypothesis that \(\mathcal{F}\) is not taut. Thus, \(\partial A(L) \neq \emptyset\). Let \(L' \subset \partial A(L)\) be a leaf. We claim \(A(L)\) cannot accumulate to \(L'\) from the negative side. If it did, there would be a sequence \(x_n \in A(L)\) converging to \(x \in L\) from the negative side, hence there would be a positively directed arc from some \(x_n\) to \(L'\). But \(x_n \in A(L)\), so there is a positively directed arc from \(L\) to \(x_n\). Combining, we obtain a positively directed arc joining \(L\) and \(L'\), forcing \(L' \subset A(L)\), contradiction. Thus, \(\overline{A(L)}\) is a compact manifold with boundary a collection of compact leaves \(L_1, \cdots, L_n\) such that \(A(L)\) lies on the negative side of all of them. Therefore, the oriented disjoint union \(L_1 \sqcup \cdots \sqcup L_n\) is null-cobordant, hence \(\chi(L_1) + \cdots + \chi(L_n) = 0\). However, we then have</p>

\[\displaystyle 0 = \int_{L_1 \sqcup \cdots \sqcup L_n} \theta = \int_{L_1} \theta + \cdots + \int_{L_n} \theta = \mathrm{vol}(L_1) + \cdots + \mathrm{vol}(L_n),\]

<p>contradiction. This concludes the proof of the theorem.</p>

<p>As an interesting application, we have the following theorem of Novikov and Rosenberg. I have attached a link to a proof I had written a while ago, which is lacking in detail but I feel gets the main ideas across. The main technical tool involves the theorem of Rummler and Sullivan above, together with a compactness theorem for minimal surfaces due to Choi-Schoen.</p>

<p><b>Theorem</b>. Let \(M^3\) be a closed oriented three-manifold. Let \(\mathcal{F}\) be a taut foliation of \(M^3\). Then the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\) are \(\pi_1\)-injective subsurfaces of \(M\). Moreover, any closed transversal to \(\mathcal{F}\) is nontrivial in \(\pi_1\).</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. See <a href="/assets/docs/taut_leaf_incomp.pdf">here</a>. The argument for closed transversals is completely analogous: we assume it is nullhomologous, therefore bounds a disk in the three-manifold by Dehn’s lemma. But then the same argument shows the disk can be homotoped rel boundary to lie entirely on a leaf, which is a contradiction.</p>

<p>We end this topic by discussing a combinatorial version of the Sullivan-Rummler theorem. First, we introduce some terminology. A normal arc in a 2-simplex is a properly embedded arc intersecting a pair of distinct edges. A normal disk in a 3-simplex is a properly embedded disk whose boundary consists of either 3 or 4 properly embedded arcs in the respective 2-faces they are contained in.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. Let \(M\) be a three-manifold with a triangulation \(\tau\). A normal surface is a surface \(S \subset M\) such that \(S\) intersects each three-simplex in \(M\) in a normal disk. A foliation \(\mathcal{F}\) on \(M\) is said to be in normal form \(\mathcal{F}\) is transverse to the 1- and 2-simplices, distinct vertices lie in distinct leaves, and for each leaf \(L\) and a three-simplex \(\Delta \subset \tau\), each non-point component of \(L \cap \Delta\) is a normal disk.</p>

<p><b>Proposition</b>. Let \(M\) be a three-manifold, and \(\mathcal{F}\) be a codimension one foliation. There exists a smooth triangulation \(\tau\) of \(M\) with respect to which \(\mathcal{F}\) is in normal form.</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Find a smooth triangulation, and then subdivide until all the three-simplices get inside foliated charts. Applying transversality, we may assume for every three-simplex \(\Delta \subset \tau\), \(\mathcal{F}\) is transverse to the 1- and 2-faces of \(\Delta\) except at some isolated points of Morse tangencies. The picture for \(\mathcal{F}\vert\Delta\) in the coordinates given by the foliated chart is that of a curvilinear simplex sitting inside \(\Bbb R^3\), getting scanned by affine linear hyperplanes \(z = \mathrm{const.}\), and the 1- and 2-faces are Morse with respect to the \(z\)-height. It’s obvious how to subdivide the simplex further to achieve normal form: add faces parallel to the level set of the \(z\)-heights at all critical values, and then tilt the new faces a little to make it transverse to the level sets except at the vertices.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. A combinatorial volume preserving flow \((\phi, \tau)\) on a three-manifold \(M\) consists of a triangulation \(\tau\) and an assignment of positive integral weights \(\phi(e)\) as well as orientation to each edge \(e \subset \tau^{(1)}\), such that at each vertex, the conservation of mass property is satisfied: sum of incoming weights is equal to sum of outgoing weights.</p>

<p>A codimension one co-oriented foliation in normal positive with a triangulation induces a natural orientation on each of the 1-skeleton: for any three-simplex, the co-orientation induces a linear ordering on the vertices of the simplex where \(v &lt; w\) if there is an edge from \(v\) to \(w\) pointing in the same direction as the co-orienting vector for the leaves transverse to that edge.</p>

<p><b>Proposition</b>. (Gabai) Let \(\mathcal{F}\) be a co-oriented codimension-one foliation on a closed oriented three-manifold \(M\). \(\mathcal{F}\) is taut if and only if there is a combinatorial volume preserving flow \((\phi, \tau)\) compatible with \(\mathcal{F}\).</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Suppose \(\mathcal{F}\) is taut, and \(\tau\) be a smooth triangulation with respect to which it is in normal form. The tautness of \(\mathcal{F}\) guarantees that the induced directed graph structure on \(\tau^{(1)}\) gives a recurrent graph, i.e., any vertex can be joined with any vertex by a piecewise linear directed arc. This is because we may take a smooth positively oriented arc in \(M\) joining them so that it is transverse to the foliation, by tautness, after which we can simplicially approximate the arc. Thus, for every edge \(e \subset \tau^{(1)}\), there is a piecewise linear directed loop \(\gamma_e \subset \tau^{(1)}\) containing \(e\). Let \(\mathcal{C} := \{\gamma_e\}\) denote a finite collection of such loops, one for each edge \(e \subset \tau^{(1)}\). We define \(\phi(e)\) to be the number of times \(\mathcal{C}\) crosses \(e\) counted with multiplicity. Then \(\phi\) clearly satisfies conservation of mass, therefore \((\phi, \tau)\) is a combinatorial volume preserving flow. The converse is easy.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. For a combinatorial volume preserving flow \((\phi, \tau)\) on \(M\) and a normal surface \(S \subset M\), we define the weight of \(S\) (to be thought as ``combinatorial area”) as</p>

\[\displaystyle w(S) = \sum_e \phi(e) |e \cap S|\]

<p>where $\vert e \cap S \vert $ denotes the cardinality of the set of intersections of $S$ with $e$.</p>

<p>Let $\mathcal{F}$ be a taut foliation with a combinatorial volume preserving flow $(\phi, \tau)$. For any leaf $L \subset \mathcal{F}$, let $S \subset L$ be a compact normal subsurface. Let $R \subset M$ be another normal surface with $\partial S = \partial R$ representing $[S] \in H_2(M, \partial S; \Bbb Z)$. Then,</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned} w(R) = \sum_e \phi(e) |e \cap R| \geq \sum_e \phi(e) \langle e, R \rangle&amp; = \sum_e \phi(e) \langle e, S \rangle \\ &amp;= \sum_e \phi(e) |e \cap S| \\ &amp;= w(S)\end{aligned}\]

<p>where $\langle e, R \rangle$ denotes the algebraic intersection number i.e., the signed intersection count. The first inequality is true as clearly the unsigned count is more than the signed count, the subsequent equality is true as $R, S$ represent the same relative homology class and the final equality is true as $S$ intersects all the edges $e$ positively by definition of the orientation of $\tau^{(1)}$ induced from the co-orientation of the leaves.</p>

<p>Therefore, the leaves of a taut foliation in normal form are combinatorial area minimizing.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="minimal-surfaces" /><category term="taut-foliations" /><category term="thurston-norm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The goal of this post is to prove the following theorem of Hansklaus Rummler and Dennis Sullivan. The references I used are “Foliations and the Geometry of 3-Manifolds” by Danny Calegari and “Combinatorial volume preserving flows and taut foliations” by David Gabai.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Monopoles and Thurston norm: Part I</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/07/monopoles-thurston-norm-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monopoles and Thurston norm: Part I" /><published>2024-03-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/07/monopoles-thurston-norm-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/07/monopoles-thurston-norm-i/"><![CDATA[<p>A couple years ago I started writing a series of posts on Seiberg-Witten invariants which I never ended up finishing (which can be found here). To tie up with what I am learning now, I’ll write some notes on the 1997 paper ``Scalar curvature and the Thurston norm” by Kronheimer and Mrowka, which exhibits an interesting connection between Seiberg-Witten theory and the Thurston norm.</p>

<p>Let us begin by recalling basic terminology. Let $M$ be an oriented closed three-manifold, equipped with a Riemannian metric $g$. A spinc (stylized  spinC ) structure on $M$ is a unitary rank $2$ vector bundle $S \to M$ together with a ``Clifford multiplication” \(\rho : TM \to \mathrm{End}(S)\) satisfying the following property: given any oriented orthonormal frame \(\{e_1, e_2, e_3\}\) at a point \(p \in M\), the following properties are true for all \(i, j\):</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\rho(e_i)\rho(e_j) + \rho(e_j)\rho(e_i) &amp;= 2\delta_{ij}I \\ \rho(e_i)^\star &amp;= -\rho(e_i) \\ \rho(e_1)\rho(e_2)\rho(e_k) &amp;= I\end{aligned}\]

<p>It can be checked that these conditions are independent of the choice of the oriented orthonormal frame. Therefore, \(\rho\) is an orientation-preserving isometric isomorphism from \(TM\) onto the subbundle of \(\mathrm{End}(S)\) denoted as \(\mathfrak{su}(S)\), consisting of traceless anti-hermitian endomorphisms, equipped with the inner product \(\mathrm{tr}(a^\star b)/2\). Any three-manifold admits a spinc structure: it is a standard fact that the tangent bundle of a three-manifold is trivial, so we define \(S = M \times \Bbb C^2\) and let \(\rho(e_i) = \sigma_i\) be the Pauli matrices, where \(\{e_1, e_2, e_3\}\) is a global orthonormal frame on \(M\). The set of spinc structures is naturally an affine space over \(H^2(M; \Bbb Z)\) for the following reason: given any class \(\alpha\) in the second cohomology group, it corresponds naturally to a complex line bundle \(L\) over \(M\) so that \(c_1(L) = \alpha\). For any spinc structure \(\mathfrak{s} = (S, \rho)\), we may form a new spinc structure \((S \otimes L, \rho \otimes 1_L)\), denoted \(\mathfrak{s} + \alpha\). In fact, it is not too difficult to see that any two spinc structures differ by an element of the second integral cohomology group.</p>

<p>Given a spinc structure \((S, \rho)\), a spinc connection is a metric connection \(B\) on \(S\) such that \(\rho\) is \(B\)-parallel, i.e., \(\nabla^B \rho = 0\). In other words, for all vector fields \(X, Y\) and section \(\psi\) of \(S\),</p>

\[\nabla^B_X (\rho(Y)\psi) = \rho(\nabla_X Y)\psi + \rho(Y) \nabla^B_X \psi,\]

<p>where \(\nabla_X Y\) is the Levi-Civita connection on \(M\). In the example \(S = M \times \Bbb C^2\) described above, we can explicitly solve for a spin connection as follows: write \(\nabla^B_X \psi = d \psi(X) + B(X) \psi\) where \(d\psi(X)\) is the directional derivative of the section \(\psi\) of \(S\) treated as a function to \(\Bbb C^2\), and \(B\) is a \(\mathfrak{u}(2)\)-valued \(1\)-form on \(M\). Then the parallelity condition above gives \([B(X), \rho(Y)] = \rho(\nabla_X Y)\). We may plug in \(X, Y\) from the oriented orthonormal basis \(\{e_1, e_2, e_3\}\) to write the trace-free part of \(B(e_i)\) completely in terms of the Pauli matrices and the Christoffel symbols. (Someone please do this computation and tell me the answer; I’ll make infinite sign errors if I try). The space of spinc connections on \((S, \rho)\) is likewise an affine space over \(\Omega^1(M; i\Bbb R)\). Indeed, for any spinc connection \(B\) and an imaginary-valued 1-form \(b\), we may form a new spinc connection \(B + b \otimes 1_S\), and any two spinc connections differ by such a 1-form. Let us call the sections of \(S\) as spinors.</p>

<p>Since \(S\) is a unitary bundle of rank \(2\), its second exterior power \(L = \Lambda^2 S\) is a line bundle with a \(\mathfrak{u}(1) (= i\mathbb{R})\)-connection induced from \(B\), which we will call \(B^t\). Indeed, \(B^t\) is the trace of the \(\mathfrak{u}(2)\)-valued form \(B\) (since the derivative of determinant is trace). Since we saw in the previous paragraph that the trace-free part of \(B^t\) is completely determined by the Levi-Civita connection on \(M\), we conclude: a spinc connection \(B\) on a fixed Riemannian manifold is entirely determined by a \(i\mathbb{R}\)-valued \(1\)-form \(B^t\). We shall denote \(F_{B^t} = dB^t\) to be the curvature of this connection on the determinant line bundle. Note that the corresponding cohomology class</p>

\[\displaystyle \left [\frac{i}{2\pi} \cdot F_{B^t} \right ] \in H^2(M; \Bbb R)\]

<p>is precisely the 1st Chern class of \(\Lambda^2 S\). We call it the Chern class of the spinc structure, and denote it by \(c_1(\mathfrak{s})\).</p>

<p>Given a spinc connection, we may form the Dirac operator on spinors, which is a linear first order partial differential operator, as follows (the definition is basis-independent):</p>

\[\displaystyle D_B : \Gamma(S) \to \Gamma(S),\; D_B\psi = \sum_{i = 1}^3 \rho(e_i)\nabla^B_{e_i} \psi\]

<p>As a final observation, note that the Clifford multiplication \(\rho\) can be extended to be defined on cotangent vectors by setting \(\rho(e^i) = \rho(e_i)\) where \(e^i\) is the dual covector to \(e_i\). We can extend it to all forms by the rule</p>

\[\displaystyle \rho(\alpha \wedge \beta) = \frac12 \left ( \rho(\alpha)\rho(\beta)+ (-1)^{|\alpha||\beta|} \rho(\beta)\rho(\alpha) \right )\]

<p>We may also define it for differential forms valued in complex coefficients, by letting \(\rho\) simply commute with complex multiplication. Now that that’s all done, let us recall the Seiberg-Witten equations on 3-manifolds.</p>

<p>Let \(M\) be a three manifold with a spinc structure \(\mathfrak{s} = (S, \rho)\). The Seiberg-Witten equations or monopole equations for a pair \((B, \psi)\) consisting of a spinc connection and a spinor are:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\frac{1}{2} \cdot \rho(F_{B^t}) &amp;= \left (\psi \otimes \psi^\star\right)_0 \\ D_B \psi &amp;= 0 \end{aligned}\]

<p>Here, \(\psi \otimes \psi^* \in S \otimes S^* = \mathrm{End}(S)\) is a linear transformation, and \((-)_0\) denotes the traceless part of it. One says a solution \((B, \psi)\) is gauge-equivalent to another solution \((B', \psi')\) if there is a function \(u : M \to S^1\) such that \(B' = B - u^{-1} du \otimes 1_S\) and \(\psi' = u \psi\). One tries to solve the monopole equations upto gauge equivalence. Observe that for any solution \((B, \psi)\), the cohomology class of \(F_{B^t}\) is unchanged under gauge equivalence. We call a solution reducible if \(\psi = 0\), which forces \(B^t\) to be flat by the first equation.</p>

<p>Notice that the equations above depend on the choice of a metric \(g\) on the Riemannian manifold \(M\). In our definition, we built the spin structure \(\mathfrak{s} = (S, \rho)\) itself using the metric. But it is not difficult to check that any two such choices of metrics \(g_0, g_1\) gives rise to isomorphic spin structures \(\mathfrak{s}_0, \mathfrak{s}_1\). This is because the space of metrics is a cone in the space of quadratic differentials, hence contractible. Thus, we can join \(g_0, g_1\) by a 1-parameter family of metrics \(g_t\). This gives rise to a 1-parameter family of spin structures \(\mathfrak{s}_t\) interpolating \(\mathfrak{s}_0, \mathfrak{s}_1\). Therefore, the spinc structure depends only upto contractible choice on the space of Riemannian metrics. Consequently, the Chern class \(c_1(\mathfrak{s})\) is certainly independent of the underlying metric. However, the Seiberg-Witten equations themselves depend on the metric, since the Dirac operator and the Clifford multiplication both depend on the metric.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. A cohomology class \(\alpha \in H^2(M; \Bbb R)\) is a monopole class if there is a spinc structure \(\mathfrak{s} = (S, \rho)\) such that \(c_1(\mathfrak{s}) = \alpha\), and the corresponding Seiberg-Witten equations have an irreducible solution for all choices of Riemannian metrics.</p>

<p>Observe that if \(c_1(\mathfrak{s}) \neq 0\), then if a solution to the Seiberg-Witten equations exist, they are necessarily irreducible. Otherwise, \((B, 0)\) is a solution, hence \(F_{B^t} = 0\), contradiction.</p>

<p>Suppose \((B, \psi)\) is an irreducible solution for the Seiberg-Witten equations with respect to some Riemannian metric \(g\) on \(M\). The linear part of the Seiberg-Witten equation tells us \(D_B \psi = 0\) (i.e., \(\psi\) is a harmonic spinor). We use the Weitzenbock-Lichnerowicz formula to deduce:</p>

\[\displaystyle 0 = D_B^\star D_B \psi = (\nabla^B)^\star \nabla^B \psi + \frac12 \rho(F_{B^t}) \psi + \frac14 s \psi,\]

<p>where \(s\) denotes the scalar curvature of \((M, g)\). The nonlinear part of the Seiberg-Witten equations imply the second term in the above is \((\psi \otimes \psi^*)_0 \psi\). We take inner product (wrt \(g\)) of the entire expression with \(\psi\). Let us compute \(\langle (\psi \otimes \psi^*)_0 \psi, \psi \rangle\). It is good to think of \(\psi\) as simply a column vector, and \(\psi \otimes \psi^*\) as simply the \(2 \times 2\) matrix \(\psi \psi^*\) where \(\psi^*\) is the conjugate-transposed row vector. Then:</p>

\[\displaystyle  \begin{aligned} \langle (\psi \otimes \psi^*)_0 \psi, \psi \rangle &amp;= \langle (\psi \psi^* - \mathrm{tr}(\psi \psi^*)/2)\psi,  \psi \rangle \\ &amp;= \langle \psi \psi^* \psi,\psi \rangle - \frac12 \mathrm{tr}(\psi \psi^*) \langle \psi, \psi \rangle \\ &amp;= \|\psi\|^4 - \frac12 \|\psi\|^4 \\ &amp;= \frac12 \|\psi\|^4 \end{aligned}\]

<p>Therefore, by using the definition of adjoint, we get:</p>

\[\displaystyle 0 = \|\nabla^B \psi\|^2 + \frac12 \|\psi\|^4 + \frac14 s \|\psi\|^2\]

<p><b>Corollary</b>. There are no irreducible solutions to the Seiberg-Witten equations for a metric \(g\) on a three-manifold of non-negative scalar curvature \(s \geq 0\). In particular, manifolds which admit a metric of non-negative scalar curvature do not possess any monopole classes.</p>

<p>Suppose the solution is irreducible. Let us integrate the above expression over the entire manifold. Ignoring the term involving the covariant derivative of \(\psi\), we get</p>

\[\displaystyle \int \frac12 \|\psi\|^4 + \frac14 \int s \|\psi\|^2 \leq 0\]

<p>Therefore,</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\int \|\psi\|^4 \leq \frac12 \int (-s) \cdot \|\psi\|^2 &amp;\leq \frac12 \left (\int s^2 \right)^{1/2} \left (\int \|\psi\|^4 \right )^{1/2} \\ \implies \int \|\psi\|^4 &amp;\leq \frac14 \int s^2\end{aligned}\]

<p>where we use that \(\psi\) is not identically zero, by irreducibility. By the nonlinear part of the Seiberg-Witten equations, we have that the norm of \(\rho(F_{B^t})/2\) is equal to the norm of \((\psi \psi^*)_0\), which we compute:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned} \|(\psi \psi^*)_0\|^2 &amp;= \frac12 \mathrm{tr} \left ( (\psi \psi^*)_0 \cdot (\psi \psi^*)_0^* \right ) \\ &amp;= \frac12 \mathrm{tr}\left (\psi \psi^* - \frac12 \|\psi\|^2 \cdot 1_S \right )^2 \\ &amp;= \frac12 \left ( \|\psi\|^4 - \frac12 \|\psi\|^4 - \frac12 \|\psi\|^4 + \frac14 \|\psi\|^4 \right ) \\ &amp;= \frac14 \|\psi\|^4 \end{aligned}\]

<p>Thus, \(\|(\psi \psi^*)_0\| = \|\psi\|^2/2\). Remember that \(\rho\) preserves norms, so we get norm of \(F_{B^t}\) with respect to \(g\) (or the inner product induced on the space of 2-forms thereof) is the same as \(\|\psi\|^2\). Therefore,</p>

\[\displaystyle \int \|F_{B^t}\|^2 = \int \|\psi\|^4 \leq \frac14 \int s^2\]

<p>Therefore, \(\|F_{B^t}\|_{L^2} \leq \|s\|_{L^2}/2\), using \(L^2\)-norms.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. Let \((M, g)\) be a Riemannian \(3\)-manifold. Recall a differential \(2\)-form \(\omega\) on the manifold is harmonic if \(d\omega = d^*\omega = 0\). Every cohomology class admits a unique harmonic representative in de Rham cohomology, by Hodge theory. We define the harmonic norm on \(H^2(M; \Bbb R)\) by setting \(\|\alpha\|_{har, g}\) to be the \(L^2\)-norm of the unique harmonic \(2\)-form representing the cohomology class \(\alpha\).</p>

<p><b>Corollary</b>. If \(\alpha \in H^2(M; \Bbb R)\) is a monopole class, then for all metrics \(g\) on \(M\),</p>

\[\displaystyle \|\alpha\|_{har, g} \leq \frac{1}{4\pi} \cdot \|s\|_{L^2(M, g)}\]

<p>This follows from what we derived as \(F_{B^t}\) represents the class \(2\pi/i \cdot \alpha\), where \(\alpha = c_1(\mathfrak{s})\) is the Chern classes associated to the spin structure we started with, and the harmonic form minimizes the \(L^2\)-norm in a given cohomology class.</p>

<p>Finally, we relate the harmonic norm with the Thurston norm for irreducible atoroidal manifolds. Since the Thurston norm is a norm defined on the second homology, we must first dualize it to a norm defined on cohomology.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. Let \(M\) be an oriented, closed, irreducible, atoroidal three-manifold with \(b_1(M) \neq 0\). We define the dual Thurston norm by setting for any \(\alpha \in H^2(M; \Bbb R)\),</p>

\[\displaystyle \|\alpha\|_{Th} = \sup_{\Sigma} \frac{|\alpha[\Sigma]|}{-\chi(\Sigma)},\]

<p>where \(\Sigma\) varies over all oriented embedded surfaces in \(M\) of genus at least \(2\).</p>

<p><b>Proposition</b>. The dual Thurston norm and the harmonic norm on an oriented, closed, irreducible, atoroidal three-manifold \(M\), satisfy the following inequality:</p>

\[\displaystyle \|\alpha\|_{Th} \leq \sup_g \frac{4\pi\|\alpha\|_{har, g}}{\|s(g)\|_{L^2(M, g)}},\]

<p>where \(g\) varies over all Riemannian metrics on \(M\) and \(s(g)\) denotes the scalar curvature of \((M, g)\).</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Let us start by fiddling around to see if we get an idea. Pick a metric \(g\) on \(M\) and let \(\Sigma\) be an embedded oriented surface of genus at least \(2\). Let \(\omega\) be a \(2\)-form representing the class \(\alpha\). Then, by the Gauss-Bonnet theorem, \(2\pi\chi(\Sigma)\) is the integral of the curvature of \(\Sigma\) with the induced metric from \((M, g)\). So,</p>

\[\displaystyle \frac{\alpha[\Sigma]}{-\chi(\Sigma)} = -\frac{2\pi\int_{\Sigma}\omega}{\int_{\Sigma} K d\mathrm{vol}_g}\]

<p>The numerator is bounded by the metric norm on \(\omega\) (which can be bounded by the harmonic norm) times the volume of \(\Sigma\), and the denominator is bounded by the \(L^2\)-norm of (half the) scalar curvature attained on \(\Sigma\) times the volume of \(\Sigma\). It seems we are awfully close, but \(a \leq b, c \leq d\) does not mean \(a/c \leq b/d\).</p>

<p>The shortcoming of this approach is that we are only focusing on the scalar curvature attained along \(\Sigma\). We must pick metrics \(g\) such that the semi-local geometry around \(\Sigma\) dominates in \(M\). Let \(g_1\) be a metric on \(M\) such that some neighborhood of \(\Sigma\) in \(M\) is isometric to \(\Sigma \times [0, 1]\) with the product metric \(dt^2 + h\), where \((\Sigma, h)\) is a hyperbolic surface of unit area. Let \(g_r\) be a radial rescaling so that in that neighborhood we have \(g_r = r^2 dt^2 + h\) and \(g_r = g_1\) outside a slightly larger neighborhood. Then the same neighborhood with the metric \(g_r\) is isometric to the product \(\Sigma \times [0, r]\). Therefore, the \(L^2\)-norm of the scalar curvature is:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned} \int s(g_r)^2 \, d\mathrm{vol}_{g_r} &amp;= \int_{\Sigma \times [0, r]} s(g_r)^2 \, d\mathrm{vol}_{g_r} + \int_{M \setminus \Sigma \times [0, 1]} s(g_1)^2 \, d\mathrm{vol}_{g_1} \\ &amp;= (-4\pi\chi(\Sigma))^2 r + C \end{aligned}\]

<p>since \(s(g_r) = 4\pi\chi(\Sigma)\) on \(\Sigma \times [0, r]\) and \(d\mathrm{vol}_{g_r} = r \, dt\,  d\mathrm{vol}_h\), and \(C\) is a constant independent of \(r\). Observe also that if \(\omega\) is any \(2\)-form representing the cohomology class \(\alpha\),</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned} |\alpha[\Sigma]|^2 \leq \left | \int_{\Sigma} \omega \right |^2 \leq \left ( \int_{\Sigma} \|\omega\|_h d\mathrm{vol}_h \right )^2 \leq \|\omega\|_{L^2(\Sigma, h)} ^2 \mathrm{Area}(\Sigma)^2 &amp;= \|\omega\|_{L^2(\Sigma, h)}^2 \\ &amp; \leq r^{-2} \|\omega\|_{L^2(M,g_r)}^2 \end{aligned}\]

<p>Therefore, we have the following equations:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned} \|s(g_r)\|_{L^2(M, g_r)} &amp;= -4\pi \chi(\Sigma) r + C' \\ \|\alpha\|_{har, g_r} &amp;\geq r |\alpha[\Sigma]|\end{aligned}\]

<p>where \(C'\) is a constant independent of \(r\). Dividing the second by the first, one obtains:</p>

\[\displaystyle \frac{\|\alpha\|_{har, g_r}}{\|s(g_r)\|_{L^2(M, g_r)}} \geq \frac{r |\alpha[\Sigma]|}{ -4\pi \chi(\Sigma) r + C'} \to \|\alpha\|_{Th}\]

<p>as \(r \to \infty\). This proves the required inequality.</p>

<p><em>Remark</em>. As \(r \to \infty\), the Riemannian manifolds \((M, g_r)\) exhibit a neck-stretching along the embedded surface \(\Sigma \subset M\), and geometrically converges to a manifold with \(\Bbb H^2 \times \Bbb R\) geometry. My guess is that if the above inequality is optimal, the equality is achieved in this limit.</p>

<p>We now tie everything together by the following theorem:</p>

<p><b>Theorem</b>. For a closed oriented irreducible atoroidal \(3\)-manifold (also known as a hyperbolic \(3\)-manifold), the monopole classes are contained in the dual Thurston norm-ball.</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Suppose \(\mathfrak{s}\) is a spinc structure with \(\alpha = c_1(\mathfrak{s})\) a monopole class. Let \(g\) be an auxiliary Riemannian metric on \(M\). Then combining the inequalities we have deduced above, we get</p>

\[\displaystyle \|\alpha\|_{Th} \leq \sup_g \frac{4\pi}{\|s(g)\|_{L^2(M, g)}} \cdot \|\alpha\|_{har, g} \leq \sup_g \frac{4\pi}{\|s(g)\|_{L^2(M, g)}} \cdot \frac{1}{4\pi} \cdot \|s(g)\|_{L^2(M, g)} = 1\]

<p>In the follow-up to this post, we will prove the converse direction. Before going there, we need to make a detour from this detour to talk about taut foliations in relation to Thurston norm, and Gabai’s theorem on existence of such.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="monopoles" /><category term="scalar-curvature" /><category term="taut-foliations" /><category term="thurston-norm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A couple years ago I started writing a series of posts on Seiberg-Witten invariants which I never ended up finishing (which can be found here). To tie up with what I am learning now, I’ll write some notes on the 1997 paper ``Scalar curvature and the Thurston norm” by Kronheimer and Mrowka, which exhibits an interesting connection between Seiberg-Witten theory and the Thurston norm.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Segue: a bit about foliations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/13/segue-foliation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Segue: a bit about foliations" /><published>2024-03-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/13/segue-foliation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/13/segue-foliation/"><![CDATA[<p>Recall that a foliation on a three-manifold is a decomposition of the manifold as a union of continuum-many disjoint, possibly noncompact subsurfaces (called leaves of the foliation), so that locally the decomposition is the standard decomposition of the three-space as a union of affine subspaces given by level sets of a linear functional. An easy example of a foliation is given by fibers of a fiber bundle \(\pi : M \to S^1\) from the three-manifold onto the circle, but not all foliations are fibers of a fibration. A famous example is the Reeb foliation, which is a foliation of the solid torus \(S^1 \times D^2\) consisting a unique compact leaf given by the boundary torus, and the rest of the leaves are embedded planes spiraling around the torus, accumulating to the boundary leaf.</p>

<div class="figure-row">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/reeb.png" height="200" width="300" />
    <figcaption>Figure. Reeb foliation as a viscous fluid flow.</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>One may double the solid torus along the boundary by \((x, y) \mapsto (y, -x)\) to obtain an interesting foliation on \(S^3\). A general recipe to produce Reeb-like foliations is: suppose \(M\) is a manifold with torus boundary and \(\mathcal{F}\) be a foliation on \(M\) by surfaces with boundary, such that the boundary of the leaves themselves foliate the boundary of the manifold \(\partial M\). Then we may “spin” the leaves around the torus as we approach the boundary to obtain a foliation on \(M\) by the spun leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\) as well as a boundary leaf \(\partial M\). These are called dead-ends, since any arc transverse to the leaves foliation from the inside is stopped by the spinning leaves from ever intersecting the boundary leaf. One may also Dehn fill \(\partial M\) by a Reeb torus to obtain closed examples.</p>

<p><b>Theorem</b>. Every three-manifold admits a foliation.</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Choose an ambient Riemannian metric on \(M\). Since \(\chi(M) = 0\), there exists a nowhere zero vector field on \(M\). Taking the orthogonal complement at each point, we obtain a plane field \(\xi\). We wish to modify \(\xi\) to be everywhere integrable and thus give rise to a foliation. To this end, let \(\mathcal{T}= \cup_i \Delta_i^3\) be a triangulation of \(M\). We use the following lemma:</p>

<p><b>Lemma</b>. (Thurston’s jiggling lemma) There exists a subdivision \(\mathcal{T}'\) of \(\mathcal{T}\) and a \(C^0\)-small perturbation \(\mathcal{T}''\) of \(\mathcal{T}'\) such that (1) \(\xi\) is transverse to the interiors of the edges and faces of \(\mathcal{T}''\) of \(\mathcal{T}'\) and (2) \(\xi\) is \(C^\infty\)-close to being horizontal on each \(3\)-simplex of \(\mathcal{T}''\) with respect to some affine coordinate system.</p>

<p><em>Proof of Lemma</em>. First, barycentric subdivide \(\mathcal{T}\) until all simplices become of arbitrarily small diameter, i.e., \(\mathrm{diam}(\Delta_i^3) &lt; \varepsilon\). Then by smoothness of \(\xi\), we may choose a coordinate system on each simplex with height coordinate \(z\) such that \(\xi\) is \(\varepsilon\)-close to \(\ker(dz)\). This ensures (2). Next, apply a crystalline subdivision procedure: embed \(\Delta^3\) in \([0, 1]^3\) as</p>

\[\Delta^3 = \{(x, y, z) \in [0, 1]^3 : x + y + z \leq 1\}\]

<p>Then slice by the hyperplanes \(\{x = k/n\}\), \(\{y = k/n\}\) and \(\{x + y + z = k/n\}\). This subdivides the simplices into uniformly small simplices such that each vertex in the one-skeleton has bounded valence. Moving the vertices up and down by small rigid motions within \([0, 1]^3\), the entire crystalline-subdivided simplex crumples up in a way that all the smaller simplices in the crystalline subdivision are of large slope and therefore transverse to the plane field \(\xi \cong \ker(dz)\), ensuring (1) as well. In retrospect, the exact model of the subdivision process is not really important for this: see figure below.</p>

<div class="figure-row">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/miura-ori.webp" height="200" width="300" />
    <figcaption>Figure. Thurston's jiggling as a Miura-ori.</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>Thus, by applying the jiggling lemma, we have made \(\xi\) transverse to the \(2\)-skeleton of the new triangulation \(\mathcal{T}''\), i.e., the “local min/max” with respect to \(\xi\) only occur at the vertices and possibly interiors of \(3\)-simplices. Remember that by construction, our \(2\)-plane field is co-oriented. Thus, the \(1\)-skeleton of the triangulation admits a directed graph structure, where we orient an edge so that it agrees with the co-orientation of the plane field. This also equips each simplex of the triangulation with a total order on the vertices so that all the edges point from a smaller vertex to a larger vertex. By a further subdivision of \(\mathcal{T}''\) if necessary, we can ensure that we can color the simplices red and blue so that adjacent simplices have different colors. We may tilt any particular red simplex so that the characteristic foliation has ``clockwise holonomy”, i.e., the leaves spiral down clockwise. Then on an adjacent blue simplex it spirals counterclockwise with respect to the natural coordinate system, by compatibility of orientation. This effect can then be inductively transported on all simplices.</p>

<div class="figure-row">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/charfoli.png" height="250" width="400" />
    <figcaption>Figure. Characteristic foliation on a simplex before and after smoothing.</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>Intersect \(\xi\) with the \(2\)-skeleton of the triangulation. On each simplex, this leaves an imprint of the plane field which is a singular (combinatorial) foliation on the boundary of the \(2\)-simplex, which we will call the characteristic foliation. It consists of exactly one minimum at the largest vertex, one maximum at the smallest vertex, and spiraling leaves connecting between them. We may extend this foliation into a neighborhood of the \(2\)-skeleton. This gives a codimension \(0\) submanifold with spherical boundaries on which the singular foliation is as described before. We would like to fill these holes by balls. This seems impossible, because of the spiraling of the leaves in the characteristic foliation. So, for each three-simplex \(\Delta^3\) with maximum vertex \(v\) and minimum vertex \(w\), we find an arc \(\tau\) transverse to the foliation joining \(v, w\) outside \(\Delta^3\). If this was possible, we could delete a neighborhood of \(\tau\) to obtain a solid torus hole with a nonsingular characteristic foliation on the boundary. Then spinning and Reeb-filling finishes the proof.</p>

<p>It remains to show that such transverse arcs \(\tau\) can in fact be constructed. To do this, recall the color-coding of the three-simplices described a paragraph ago. Suppose \(\Delta^3\) is a red simplex. Then the characteristic foliation has clockwise holonomy. The strategy is to take an arc \(\tau\) joining \(v, w\) in \(\partial \Delta^3\) transverse to the singular foliation with anti-clockwise holonomy, so that it is transverse to all the leaves. Then we could take a push-off of \(\tau\) so that the interior of \(\tau\) is disjoint from \(\Delta^3\).</p>

<p>This has a problem, in that the picture of the characteristic foliation in the above figure is ``wrong”. If the characteristic foliation was infinitely spiraling near the max/min vertices \(v, w\) as in the picture, we would not be able to extend it inwards on a regular neighborhood because of the singularity. We need to modify the plane field (or the coordinate system) so that near \(v, w\) the characteristic foliation is by concentric circles (or triangles, before smoothening), and outside a little neighborhood we have the spiraling pattern, to be able to extend to a smooth foliation in a regular neighborhood of the \(2-\)skeleton. But now we have a problem with constructing the arc \(\tau\) near \(v, w\). To solve this problem, we observe that there is an adjacent blue simplex such that \(v, w\) are one of the non-extremal vertices of this simplex. We start the arc \(\tau\) by going from \(v\) into this adjacent simplex, spiral downwards in counterclockwise fashion by following the singular foliation, come back to \(\Delta^3\) and follow our transverse arc counterclockwise to the characteristic foliation on \(\partial \Delta^3\), and once we are sufficiently close to \(w\), go back out into the adjacent simplex and follow its characteristic foliation again until coming back to \(w\) from the outside. Taking a push-off of this satisfies the required transversality property.</p>

<p><em>Remark</em>. An analogous proof shows that all three-manifolds admit a contact structure, but its easier because the figure above for the characteristic foliation on the sphere is not wrong, and finding transverse arcs are much easier in contact topology. This also shows that any plane field can be homotoped to a foliation (respectively, contact structure). See, “Confoliations” by Thurston and Eliashberg for more.</p>

<p>OK, every three-manifold has a foliation. But what if we changed the rules so that you cannot cheat?</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. A foliation \(\mathcal{F}\) is taut if there exists an closed curve \(\gamma\) transversely intersecting all the leaves of \(\mathcal{F}\).</p>

<p>This immediately rules out existence of Reeb components and dead-end components. So the proof above, which heavily relied on filling toroidal holes by Reeb foliations, breaks completely. So which three-manifolds admit taut foliations? Some immediate examples are that of fibered manifolds in the beginning of the post. We give an example of a taut foliation which is not fibered.</p>

<p><em>Example</em>. Let \(f : \Sigma \to \Sigma\) be a diffeomorphism of a surface of genus \(g \geq 2\). Let \(M = T(f)\) be the mapping torus of \(f\), which admits an obvious fibering \(\pi : M \to S^1\) by construction. We shall modify the fibering to be a rather complicated taut foliation, as follows. Consider \(\Sigma \times [0, 1]\) with the standard foliation by \(\Sigma \times \{x\}\). Let \(C \subset \Sigma\) be any non-separating essential curve, for instance, a meridian. Then the annulus \(C \times [0, 1]\) intersects all the leaves of the standard height foliation transversely. We cut \(\Sigma \times [0, 1]\) open along \(C \times [0, 1]\), so that every leaf becomes a surface of genus \(1\) with two punctures.</p>

<div class="figure-row">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/depthfol.png" height="190" width="500" />
    <figcaption>Figure. Messing up a fibering.</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>Let \(h : [0, 1] \to [0, 1]\) be a homeomorphism such that \(0, 1\) are fixed points of \(h\), such that \(0\) is an attracting fixed point. We now ``cross-glue” the cut open \(\Sigma \times [0, 1]\) along \(C \times [0, 1]\) by \(h\), so that the cut-open leaves at different heights glue among themselves. Since \(h(0) = 0\) is an attracting fixed points, we will see infinite-genus surface leaves accumulating to \(\Sigma \times \{0\}\) in the resulting foliation. We glue the top and bottom by \(f\) to get back \(M\) with a new foliation that is definitely not fibered. Moreover, since the cutting-repasting operation does nothing to the foliation on one side, there is a closed transversal all the same: see the green arc above.</p>

<p>However, this only gives examples of interesting taut foliations on the class of fibered three-manifolds. Eventually, I would like to describe Gabai’s construction of taut foliations on many more three-manifolds (in fact, one just needs the first betti number to be positive). For now, in the next post we shall discuss the geometry of taut foliations: Sullivan’s theorem (topologically taut implies geometrically taut) and what it has to do with max-flow-min-cut. And then return to the Thurston norm, eventually.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="3-manifolds" /><category term="contact-topology" /><category term="taut-foliations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recall that a foliation on a three-manifold is a decomposition of the manifold as a union of continuum-many disjoint, possibly noncompact subsurfaces (called leaves of the foliation), so that locally the decomposition is the standard decomposition of the three-space as a union of affine subspaces given by level sets of a linear functional. An easy example of a foliation is given by fibers of a fiber bundle \(\pi : M \to S^1\) from the three-manifold onto the circle, but not all foliations are fibers of a fibration. A famous example is the Reeb foliation, which is a foliation of the solid torus \(S^1 \times D^2\) consisting a unique compact leaf given by the boundary torus, and the rest of the leaves are embedded planes spiraling around the torus, accumulating to the boundary leaf.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thurston norm: Part II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/12/thurston-norm-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thurston norm: Part II" /><published>2024-03-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-03-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/12/thurston-norm-ii</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/12/thurston-norm-ii/"><![CDATA[<p><b>Theorem</b>. (Thurston) Suppose \((M, \partial M)\) is a compact oriented \(3\)-manifold-with-boundary, and every embedded surface representing a nonzero homology class has negative Euler characteristic. Then the Thurston norm-ball of \((M, \partial M)\) is a finite-sided convex polyhedron.</p>

<p>The hypothesis of the theorem implies the Thurston norm is in fact a norm, as opposed to a semi-norm. Note that this is satisfied, for instance, if \(M\) is a hyperbolic \(3\)-manifold with boundary. The theorem will follow from the following lemma about normed spaces, with \(V = H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb R)\) as the vector space and \(\Lambda\) as the integral lattice given by image of the change of coefficients homomorphism from the integral cohomology.</p>

<p><b>Lemma</b>. Let \(V\) is a finite-dimensional real vector space and \(\Lambda \subset V\) is an integer lattice. Let \(\\| \cdot\\|\) be a norm on \(V\) and suppose \(\\| \cdot\\|\) takes integer values on \(\Lambda\). Then the unit ball in \((V, \\| \cdot\\| )\) is a finite-sided convex polyhedron.</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>.  For ease of discussion, suppose \(V = \Bbb R^3\) and \(\Lambda = \Bbb Z^3\). Whenever \(\alpha, \beta, \gamma\) are an integral basis of \(\Bbb R^3\), there is a unique linear functional \(L_{\alpha, \beta, \gamma}\) on \(\Bbb R^3\) with integer coefficients such that its values at \(\alpha, \beta, \gamma\) are \(\\| \alpha\\| , \\| \beta\\| , \\| \gamma\\|\), respectively. Let \(\mathbf{e}_i, 1 \leq i \leq 3\) denote the standard integral basis of \(\Bbb Z^3\). Let us denote \(L_n := L_{\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1}\). We observe:</p>

\[\displaystyle L_n(\mathbf{e}_3) = L_n(\mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1) - n L_n(\mathbf{e}_1) = \\| \mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1\\|  - n \\| \mathbf{e}_1\\| ,\]

<p>which is non-increasing in \(n\), by the triangle inequality. But as this value is integral, we conclude \(L_n(\mathbf{e}_3)\) must be eventually constant. Therefore, for some sufficiently large \(n\), \(L_n(\mathbf{e}_3) = L_{n+1}(\mathbf{e}_3)\), which translates to:</p>

\[\\| \mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1\\|  + \\| \mathbf{e}_1\\|  = \\| (\mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1) + \mathbf{e}_1\\|\]

<p>Now, it is a property of any norm \(\| \cdot\|\) on a vector space \(V\) that if \(x, y \in V\) are two points such that one has \(\| x + y\|  = \| x\|  + \| y\|\), then \(\| \cdot\|\) is a linear function on the entire Euclidean line segment connecting \(x, y\). This can be checked by the following tricky triangle inequality argument: suppose \(t \in [0, 1]\), then</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\| x + y\|  = \| x + ty + (1 - t)y\|  \leq \| x + ty\|  + (1-t)\| y\|  &amp;\leq \| x\|  + t\| y\|  +(1-t)\| y\|  \\ &amp;= \| x\|  + \| y\| \end{aligned}\]

<p>By hypothesis the first and last terms in the above chain of inequalities are equal, which means all the intermediate inequalities must be equality. Therefore, \(\| x + ty\|  = \| x\|  + t\| y\|\), as desired. As a corollary of this, we obtain \(\\| \cdot\\|\) is linear along the Euclidean segment connecting \(\mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1\) and \(\mathbf{e}_1\). Therefore, \(\\| \cdot\\|\) agrees with \(L_n\) along this segment. Now, consider the linear function \(L_{m, n} := L_{\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2 + m \mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1}\). Notice \(L_{m, n}\) agrees with \(L_n\) on \(\mathbf{e}_3\), and by an analogous argument as earlier, \(L_{m, n}(\mathbf{e}_2)\) is eventually constant for large enough values of \(m\). Therefore, for some sufficiently large \(m\), \(L_{m, n}(\mathbf{e}_2) = L_{m+1,n}(\mathbf{e}_2)\) and so \(\\| \cdot\\|\) agrees with \(L_{m, n}\) on the Euclidean segment connecting \(\mathbf{e}_2 + m \mathbf{e}_1\) and \(\mathbf{e}_1\). Finally, consider</p>

\[\displaystyle L_{m, n, p} = L_{\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_2 + m \mathbf{e}_1 + p(\mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e_1}) + p \mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_3 + n \mathbf{e}_1}\]

<p>Let us write \(\alpha = \mathbf{e}_1\), \(\beta = \mathbf{e}_2 + m\mathbf{e}_1\) and \(\gamma = \mathbf{e}_3 + n\mathbf{e}_1\) for brevity. Mutatis mutandis, we conclude that \(L_{m, n, p}\) agrees with \(L_{m, n, p+1}\) for large enough values of \(p\). Consequently, for a sufficiently large value of \(p\), we must have \(\displaystyle L_{m, n, p}(\beta) = L_{m, n, p+1}(\beta)\). Simplifying, we get</p>

\[\\| \beta+ p \gamma + p \alpha\\|  + \\| \gamma + \alpha\\|  = \\| \beta + (p+1)\gamma + (p+1)\alpha\\|\]

<p>But observe \(\\| \gamma + \alpha\\|  = \\| \mathbf{e}_3 + (n+1)\mathbf{e}_1\\|  = \\| \gamma\\|  + \\| \alpha\\|\). Using this, we deduce,</p>

\[\\| \beta+ p \gamma + p \alpha\\|  + \\| \gamma\\|  + \\| \alpha\\|  = \\| (\beta + p\gamma + p\alpha) + \gamma + \alpha\\|\]

<p>For any triple of vectors \(x, y, z\) in a normed vector space \((V, \| \cdot\| )\), if \(\| x +y+z\|  = \| x\| +\| y\| +\| z\|\) holds, then \(\| \cdot\|\) is in fact linear on the entire simplex spanned by \(x, y, z\). This follows from an analogous argument as in the segment case: for all \(t, s \in [0, 1]\),</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\| x + y + z\|  &amp;= \| x + ty + sz + (1 - t)y + (1-s)z\|   \\ &amp;\leq \| x + ty + sz\|  + (1-t)\| y\|  + (1-s)\| z\|  \\&amp;= \| x\|  + \| y\|  + \| z\| \end{aligned}\]

<p>By hypothesis, all the inequalities above are equalities. Applying this with</p>

\[x = \beta+p\gamma+p\alpha, y = \gamma, z = \alpha,\]

<p>we see \(L_{m, n, p}\) agrees with \(\\| \cdot\\|\) on the entire simplex spanned by these vectors. Therefore, the hyperplane \(\{L_{m, n, p} = 1\}\) defines a facet of the unit norm ball, by convexity of the ball. Notice that \(L_{m, n, p}\) is an integral linear functional, and norm of \(L_{m, n, p}\) with respect to \(\\| \cdot\\|\) is \(1\) as it is tangential to the unit norm ball, and the rest of the ball lies on the half-space \(L_{m, n, p} \leq 1\). Varying \(\mathbf{e}_i\), \(1 \leq i \leq 3\) over all integral bases of \(\Bbb Z^3\) by an action of \(\mathrm{SL}_3(\Bbb Z)\), we see that that the vectors \(\beta + p\gamma+p\alpha\), \(\gamma\) and \(\alpha\) can define all projectively rational simplices in \(\Bbb{RP}^2\). Therefore, the unit norm ball of \(\\| \cdot\\|\) is intersection of half-spaces defined by integral linear functionals of norm \(1\). Since the dual norm ball is compact, we conclude the norm ball must be a finite intersection of half-space defined by integral linear functionals. This concludes the proof.</p>

<p>As a consequence, we give a solution to the exercise at the end of the previous post. Let \(L \subset S^3\) be the Whitehead link, and \(\alpha, \beta\) be the generators of \(H_2(S^3 \setminus \nu(L), \partial \nu(L); \Bbb Z)\) as before. We wish to find a norm-minimizing representative of \(5 \alpha + 3 \beta\). Recall we proved,</p>

\[\\| \alpha\\|  = \\| \beta\\|  = \\| (\alpha + \beta)/2\\|  = 1,\]

<p>where \(\alpha + \beta\) has norm \(2\) because this is the homology class of the Seifert surface of the Whitehead link, which is genus \(1\) and therefore Euler characteristic \(2 - 2 \cdot 1 - 2 = -2\) (as there are two components). By the Theorem above, we conclude that the entire segment connecting \(\alpha, \beta\) in the real homology vector space must be contained in the unit sphere of the Thurston norm. Hence, the convex combination \(5/8 \cdot \alpha + 3/8 \cdot \beta\) must have norm \(1\). Thus, \(\\| 5 \alpha + 3 \beta\\|  = 8\).</p>

<p>To find a minimizing representative, we simply consider \(5\) parallel copies of the surface \(\alpha\), and \(3\) parallel copies of the surface \(\beta\). A pair of surfaces chosen from each intersect in a properly embedded arc (connecting a pair of points in the two components of \(L\)). We take the oriented sum of the surfaces, by cutting both along the arc and pasting criss-cross so that orientations are preserved. Doing this for all arcs in the intersection resolves the singularities. This is the desired norm-minimizer, as can be checked by computing the Euler characteristic.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hyperbolic-geometry" /><category term="taut-foliations" /><category term="contact-topology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Theorem. (Thurston) Suppose \((M, \partial M)\) is a compact oriented \(3\)-manifold-with-boundary, and every embedded surface representing a nonzero homology class has negative Euler characteristic. Then the Thurston norm-ball of \((M, \partial M)\) is a finite-sided convex polyhedron.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thurston norm: Part I</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/28/thurston-norm-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thurston norm: Part I" /><published>2024-02-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-02-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/28/thurston-norm-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/28/thurston-norm-i/"><![CDATA[<p>Let \((M, \partial M)\) be a compact, oriented \(3\)-manifold. We shall say a compact surface \((S, \partial S) \subset M\) is properly embedded if \(S \subset M\) is an embedded surface and \(\partial S \subset \partial M\) is a collection of embedded curves. A properly embedded oriented surface may be triangulated to obtain a singular \(2\)-cycle relative to \(\partial M\), which represents its fundamental class \([(S, \partial S)] \in H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z)\). Conversely, suppose we have a class \(\alpha \in H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z)\). Then its Poincare dual \(\mathrm{PD}(\alpha)\) gives rise to a map \(\phi : M \to S^1\) by chasing the sequence isomorphisms:</p>

\[\displaystyle H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z) \cong H^1(M, \Bbb Z) \cong \mathrm{Hom}(\pi_1(M), \Bbb Z) \cong [M, S^1]\]

<p>Let \(p \in S^1\) be a regular value of \(\phi\). Then \(S = \phi^{-1}(p)\) satisfies \([(S, \partial S)] = \alpha\). One might then ask what is the minimum possible complexity of a surface representing a given relative second homology class. One measure of such a complexity is genus, but since our surfaces have boundary, we would like to consider the negative part of the Euler characteristic instead.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. For \(\alpha \in H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z)\), the Thurston norm of \(\alpha\) is defined as</p>

\[\displaystyle \|\alpha\| = \mathrm{inf}_S \sum_{S_i \subset S} \max\{0, -\chi(S_i)\},\]

<p>where \(S\) varies over all surfaces such that \(\alpha = [(S, \partial S)]\) and \(S_i\) are connected components of \(S\).</p>

<p>Notice that sphere, disk, annulus and torus components of a surface contribute nothing to the norm. In some sense, this is intentional: one is searching for surfaces of minimal complexity to cut \(M\) along after it has already been cut along all the two-sided incompressible spheres (i.e., prime decomposition) and a minimal collection of two-sided incompressible tori (i.e., JSJ decomposition).  Nevertheless, formally ignoring these cases by not assigning them any importance in the norm allows one to define it in full generality.</p>

<p><b>Observation</b>. Let \(M\) be irreducible (i.e., all embedded spheres either bound a ball or are boundary-parallel). If \((S, \partial S) \subset M\) realizes Thurston norm in its homology class (we shall say: \((S, \partial S)\) minimizes the norm), then \(S\) is incompressible.</p>

<p><em>Proof</em>. Suppose not. Irreducibility guarantees we can assume there are no spherical components. Then there must be a closed curve \(\gamma \subset S\) which is not nullhomotopic in \(S\), but is nullhomotopic in \(M\). Then the loop theorem implies \(\gamma\) must also bound a disk \(D\) (called a “compressing disk”) in $M$. Consider a thickening of $S \cup D \subset M$ and take one of the boundary components to obtain a “compression” of \(S\) along \(D\), which we shall call \(S'\). Note \(\chi(S') = \chi(S) + 2\). If \(\gamma\) is non-separating, we observe that \(S'\) cannot be a sphere by irreducibility of \(M\). If \(\gamma\) is separating, say \(S' = S_1' \cup S_2'\), then \(S_1', S_2'\) cannot be spheres as \(\gamma \subset S\) is essential. Therefore, \((S', \partial S')\) has total negative Euler characteristic strictly less than that of \((S, \partial S)\), contradicting the hypothesis that \((S, \partial S)\) is a norm-minimizer.</p>

<p><em>Remark</em>. A surface \((S, \partial S) \subset M\) is said to be boundary-compressible if there is an embedded disk \(D \subset M\) (called a “boundary-compressing disk”) such that $\partial D = \alpha \cup \beta$ is a union of a pair of arcs sharing endpoints such that $D \cap S = \alpha$ is an essential arc in $S$ and $D \cap \partial M = \beta$. Since compressing along a boundary compressing disk is tantamount to cutting $S$ along $\alpha$, the result is a surface $S’$ such that $\chi(S’) = \chi(S) + 1$. If $M$ is boundary-irreducible (i.e., $\partial M$ has no spherical components and is $\pi_1$-injective in $M$), we can rule out disk components in $S’$ by an analogous argument as above. Therefore, in this case the norm-minimizing surfaces must also be boundary-incompressible.</p>

<p>Why stop here? We may define for any rational class $\alpha \in H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Q)$, $|\alpha| = |k \alpha|/k$ where $k$ is an integer so that $k\alpha$ is integral. We may even extend $|\cdot|$ to all of $H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb R)$: simply write a real class as a real linear combination of an integral basis of $H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z)$, and approximate the coefficients by rationals. There are two things to be checked in order to ensure this is well-defined:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Is it true that $|k[S]|=k|[S]|$ for integer $k$?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Is it true that $|[S] + [S’]| \leq |[S]| + |[S’]|$?</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Check 1</em>. Suppose $S’ = \phi^{-1}(p)$ is a surface that represents $k[S]$, where $\phi :M \to S^1$ corresponds to the class $k \mathrm{PD}[S] \in H^1(M; \Bbb Z)$. This map lifts along the $k$-fold covering map $S^1 \to S^1$. Let us denote the lift as $\tilde{\phi} : M \to S^1$. Then $S$ is disjoint union of the surfaces $S_i = \tilde{\phi}^{-1}(p_i)$, $1 \leq i \leq k$, each in the homology class of $[S]$. Moreover, if we choose $S’$ to be a norm-minimizer, each connected component $S_i$ has to be a norm-minimizer as well. Thus, $|k[S]| = k |[S]|$.</p>

<p><em>Check 2</em>. Suppose $M$ is irreducible and $\partial M = \emptyset$. We choose $S, S’$ to be norm-minimizers, which implies they are incompressible by an earlier observation. We put the surfaces in general position. Note that $S \cap S’$ consists of disjoint simple closed curves as $S, S’ \subset M$ are embedded. Suppose $\gamma$ is a closed curve in the intersection which is nullhomotopic in $M$, then by incompressibility it is nullhomotopic in both $S, S’$. Without loss of generality, say $\gamma$ is innermost in $S$, i.e., there’s no other loop in the Jordan disk bounded by $\gamma$ in $S$ that is in the intersection locus $S \cap S’$. The sphere co-bounded by the disk bounding $\gamma$ in $S, S’$ respectively bounds a ball by irreducibility of $M$, and we may push $S$ to the boundary of the ball to reduce the cardinality of the intersection locus. After doing this finitely many times, we are left with an intersection locus consisting only of disjoint simply closed curves which are essential in both $S$ and $S’$. The local picture near the intersection is the same as $\mathbf{X} \times S^1$ where $\mathbf{X}$ is the letter X. We replace this by $\pmb{)(} \times S^1$ in a way that the resulting surface is oriented. The resulting surface $S’’$ is obtained by cutting $S, S’$ along certain disjoint essential simple closed curves and gluing along the seams. Therefore, $\chi(S’’) = \chi(S) +\chi(S’)$. Moreover, no component of $S’’$ can be a sphere, as that would imply one of the seams in $S$ or $S’$ is non-essential. Observe $S’’$ represents the homology class $[S] + [S’]$. Therefore, $|[S] +[S’]| \leq |[S]| + |[S’]|$, as desired. If $\partial M \neq \emptyset$, and $M$ is irreducible and boundary-irreducible, then from the remark below the observation above, we may likewise conclude the same inequality.</p>

<p>The verifications above implies $| \cdot |$ is a well-defined semi-norm on $H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Q)$ and as such can be continuously extended to a semi-norm on $H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb R)$. Note that if $(M, \partial M)$ is a hyperbolic $3$-manifold with cuspidal boundary, this is in fact a norm, as there cannot be any essential spheres, tori, disks or annuli inside the manifold, which are precisely the surfaces on which the Thurston norm vanishes.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. The Thurston norm-ball of $(M, \partial M)$ is defined to be the unit ball in $H^2(M, \partial M; \Bbb R)$ under the Thurston norm.</p>

<div class="figure-row">
  <figure>
    <img src="/assets/images/norm-ball-whitehead.png" height="350" width="350" />
    <figcaption>Figure: Thurston norm-ball for the Whitehead link.</figcaption>
  </figure>
</div>

<p>As an example, we try to compute the Thurston norm for the complement $S^3 \setminus \nu(L)$ of the Whitehead link $L \subset S^3$. The real homology of the complement is a real vector space of rank $2$, generated by Poincare dual to the meridians of each of the components $K_1, K_2$ indicated in the picture. These are given by the thrice-punctured sphere $\alpha$ bounded by $K_1$, and the punctured torus $\beta$ bounded by $K_2$, respectively, indicated by the red and blue surfaces in the picture. Each of these have Euler characteristic $-1$ and are norm-minimizing, so they are in the unit sphere for the Thurston norm. Symmetrically, $-\alpha, -\beta$ are also elements in the unit sphere. In the picture we also have a green dot which corresponds to the class of $(\alpha + \beta)/2$. Note that $\alpha + \beta$ is represented by the surface drawn in green, given by an oriented sum of the surfaces $\alpha$ and $\beta$. This is a “Seifert surface” for the Whitehead link, and its Euler characteristic is \(-2\) (sum of the ones for \(\alpha, \beta\)). In fact, we shall show next time that the entire line segment connecting \((1, 0)\) and \((0, 1)\) is contained in the unit sphere. Therefore, the unit norm-ball is the magenta diamond above.</p>

<p>Exercise. Can you imagine a norm-minimizing representative of \(2 \alpha + \beta\)? How about \(5 \alpha + 3 \beta\)?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hyperbolic-geometry" /><category term="taut-foliations" /><category term="contact-topology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let \((M, \partial M)\) be a compact, oriented \(3\)-manifold. We shall say a compact surface \((S, \partial S) \subset M\) is properly embedded if \(S \subset M\) is an embedded surface and \(\partial S \subset \partial M\) is a collection of embedded curves. A properly embedded oriented surface may be triangulated to obtain a singular \(2\)-cycle relative to \(\partial M\), which represents its fundamental class \([(S, \partial S)] \in H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z)\). Conversely, suppose we have a class \(\alpha \in H_2(M, \partial M; \Bbb Z)\). Then its Poincare dual \(\mathrm{PD}(\alpha)\) gives rise to a map \(\phi : M \to S^1\) by chasing the sequence isomorphisms:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The h-principle for Legendrian immersions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/17/h-principle-legendrian/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The h-principle for Legendrian immersions" /><published>2022-05-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/17/h-principle-legendrian</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/17/h-principle-legendrian/"><![CDATA[<p>Consider a bicycle on a 2-dimensional cartesian plane. We will choose coordinates \((x, y)\) for the position of the bicycle, and angle \(\theta\) that the steering wheel makes with the \(x\)-axis. In other words, our model of the bicycle has three degrees of freedom, two of them given by position in \(\Bbb R^2\) and the other given by the angle of the steering wheel in \(S^1\). Thus, the configuration space of the bicycle is \(M = \Bbb R^2 \times S^1\). The trajectory of such a bicycle in motion \(\gamma(t) = (x(t), y(t))\) on \(\Bbb R^2\) must have tangent \(\gamma'(t)\) parallel to the direction \((\cos \theta(t), \sin \theta(t))\) of the steering wheel. In other words, the motion of the bicycle is constrained by the differential relation \(\dot{x} \cos(\theta) - \dot{y} \sin(\theta) = 0\) on \(M\). The relation can be described as a rank 2 subbundle \(\xi \subset TM\) given by kernel \(\xi = \ker \alpha\) of a differential \(1\)-form \(\alpha = \cos(\theta) dx - \sin(\theta) dy\) on \(M\). Motions of trajectories of the bicycle are therefore paths \(\gamma\) in \(M\) which are parallel to the distribution \(\xi\), i.e., \(\gamma' \in \xi\).</p>

<p>The situation here is the simplest example of a so-called contact manifold. A contact manifold is a manifold \(M\) of odd dimension \(\dim M = 2n+1\) equipped with a \(1\)-form \(\alpha\) which is completely nonintegrable, i.e., \(\alpha \wedge (d\alpha)^{\wedge n}\) is nowhere-vanishing. Contact manifolds are studied upto contactomorphisms, which are diffeomorphisms preserving the conformal class of the contact \(1\)-forms. Therefore, contactomorphisms preserve the associated hyperplane distribution \(\xi = \ker \alpha\), which carries with it a conformal class of a fiberwise symplectic structure given by \(d\alpha\); we denote this class by \(\mathrm{CS}(\xi)\). It is a theorem that any contact manifold is locally contactomorphic to \((\Bbb R^{2n+1}, \xi_0)\) where</p>

\[\xi_0 = \ker(dz - \sum_{i = 1}^n y_i dx_i)\]

<p>This can be seen in the bicycle example, as one can locally scale appropriately so that the form becomes \(dx - \tan(\theta) dy\) and use \(\tan(\theta)\) as a coordinate. Contact manifolds are the odd-dimensional counterparts to symplectic manifolds, which typically occur in physics as phase spaces \(T^*Q\) of a manifold \(Q\). The analogous example in the contact world is the \(1\)-jet space \(J^1 Q = \Bbb R \times T^* Q\), where the contact form is defined by \(dz - \sum_i p_i dq_i\) where \(p_i, q_i\) are the generalized position and momentum coordinates of the phase space. Note that \(\sum_i p_i dq_i\) is the tautological \(1\)-form on \(T^* Q\), and its exterior derivative \(\sum_i dp_i \wedge dq_i\) is exactly the symplectic form on the phase space. Functions \(f : Q \to \Bbb R\) give rise to Lagrangian submanifolds of \(T^* Q\) given by image of the exact \(1\)-form considered as a section \(df : Q \to T^* Q\). Likewise, functions \(f : Q \to \Bbb R\) give rise to certain special submanifolds of \(J^1 Q\) given by image of the \(1\)-jet prolongation \(J^1(f) : Q \to J^1 Q\). These are called Legendrian submanifolds; we give a general definition below.</p>

<p>An immersion \(f : N \to (M^{2n+1}, \xi)\) into a contact manifold is called isotropic if \(f\) is \(\xi\)-parallel, i.e., \(df\) maps \(TN\) to \(\xi\). This imposes the condition that \(\dim N \leq n\), and we say \(f\) is Legendrian if the equality \(\dim N = n\) is achieved. Since \(3 = 2 \cdot 1 + 1\), the trajectories of motion of a bicycle were Legendrian paths in \(\Bbb R^2 \times S^1\). Bicycle tracks have interesting properties: despite being constrained by a closed differential relation (in this case, a differential equation), one can travel from any point to any other point using a bicycle (that’s part of the point of a bicycle, really…). Not only that, but it’s possible to carry out impressive maneuvers to navigate through virtually any set of obstacles. The following theorem might shed some light into this phenomenon. Let us call a pair \((F, f) : (TN, N) \to (TM, M)\) of maps to be a formal Legendrian immersion if \(F\) is a bundle monomorphism covering \(f\) and \(F\) is fiberwise Legendrian (guess what this means). Any Legendrian immersion \(f\) gives rise to a formal Legendrian immersion \((df, f)\), and to distinguish this sub-class of formal immersions we call them holonomic. When we speak of homotopies, we shall think of them as happening inside this “space” of formal Legendrian immersions. We also equip \(M\) with an arbitrary ambient Riemannian metric.</p>

<p><b>Theorem</b>. Any formal Legendrian immersion is homotopic to a holonomic Legendrian immersion by a \(C^0\)-small homotopy. The result is also true for</p>
<ol>
  <li>CW-complex parametrized families of Legendrian immersions and</li>
  <li>relative to submanifolds on which the formal immersions are already holonomic.</li>
</ol>

<p>We will deduce this from Eliashberg-Mishachev’s holonomic approximation theorem. The form of the theorem we shall need is the following. Let \(X \to V\) be a fiber bundle, \(\mathcal{R} \subset X^{(r)}\) be a subset of the total space of the associated \(r\)-jet bundle, called a differential relation of order \(r\) (for example, the constraint on bicycle trajectories can be viewed as a differential relation of order \(1\)). Sections \(V \to X^{(r)}\) which land inside \(\mathcal{R}\) will be called formal sections of \(\mathcal{R}\), and among these, those which come from \(r\)-jet prolongation of a section \(V \to X\) will be called holonomic sections. We shall introduce two important properties of a differential relation before stating the theorem: Let \(\phi : I^k \to V\) be a continuous map, \(\{f_t : \{\phi(t)\} \to V : t \in I^k\}\) a continuous family of formal sections and \(\{\widetilde{f}_t : \mathrm{Op}(\phi(t)) \to V : t \in \partial I^k\}\) be a family of holonomic extensions of \(f_t\) for \(t \in \partial I^k\). Then we say \(\mathcal{R}\) is (parametrically) locally integrable if there exists a continuous family of holonomic extensions \(\{\widetilde{f}_t : \mathrm{Op}(\phi(t)) \to V : t \in I^k\}\) agreeing with the earlier family for all \(t \in \partial I^k\). For \(k = 0\), note that this simply says every jet in \(\mathcal{R}\) is value of the \(r\)-jet prolongation of some section of \(\mathcal{R}\) at the basepoint. Let \(D^k \times D^{n-k} \cong H\) denote a handle, and let \(C = D^k \times \{0\} \subset H\) denote the core. Let \(\phi : H \times I^m \to V\) be an isotopy, and let \(H_t := \phi(H \times \{t\})\), \(C_t := \phi(C \times \{t\}) \subset H_t\) for all \(t \in I^m\). Suppose we are given (a) a family of germs of holonomic sections \(\{f_t : \mathrm{Op}(H_t) \to \mathcal{R}\}\) near the handles, and (b) a family-homotopy of germs of holonomic sections \(\{f_{t, s} : \mathrm{Op}(\partial H_t \cup C_t) \to \mathcal{R}\}\), \(s \in [0, 1]\) near the union of the boundary and the core of the handles, such that \(f_t\) extends \(f_{t, 0}\), and \(\{f_{t, s}\}\) is a constant in \(s\) on \(\mathrm{Op}(\partial H_t \cap C_t)\). The relation \(\mathcal{R}\) is said to be (parametrically) microflexible if there exists \(\varepsilon &gt; 0\), depending on \(\phi\) and the data given, such that there is a homotopy of germs of holonomic sections \(\widetilde{f}_{t, s} : \mathrm{Op}(H_t) \to \mathcal{R}\), \(s \in [0, \varepsilon]\) extending the given data while staying constant on \(\mathrm{Op}(\partial H_t \cap C_t)\).</p>

<p><b>Theorem</b>. (Eliashberg-Mishachev) \(\mathcal{R} \subset X^{(r)}\) be a locally integrable microflexible differential relation of order \(r\). Let \(K \subset V\) be a positive codimension subcomplex and \(f : \mathrm{Op}(K) \to \mathcal{R}\) be a germ of a formal section. Then for any arbitrarily small \(\delta, \varepsilon &gt; 0\), there exists a diffeotopy \(\{h_t : V \to V\}\) which is \(\delta\)-small in \(C^0\)-norm, and a holonomic section \(\widetilde{f} : \mathrm{Op}(h_1(K)) \to \mathcal{R}\) such that \(\widetilde{f}, f\) are uniformly \(\varepsilon\)-close on \(\mathrm{Op}(h_1(K)) \subset \mathrm{Op}(K)\).</p>

<p>Suppose \((M, \xi_M), (N, \xi_N)\) are two contact manifolds. An immersion \(f : M \to N\) is called isocontact if \(f^*\mathrm{CS}(\xi_N) = \mathrm{CS}(\xi_M)\). A map from \(M\) to \(N\) is equivalently a section of the product bundle \(X = M \times N\) over \(M\), and the property of being an isocontact immersion can be formulated as a differential relation \(\mathcal{R} \subset X^{(1)}\). \(\mathcal{R}\) is locally integrable by Gray’s stability theorem, as any linear isocontact embedding can be exponentiated to contact charts. \(\mathcal{R}\) is also microflexible, as the contact isotopy extension theorem holds with no restrictions (an interesting remark here is that the same cannot be said for the isosymplectic version, as the symplectic isotopy extension demands \(H^2(H, \partial H \cup C) = 0\) which is true iff \(H\) is not a \(1\)-handle.) Thus, holonomic approximation theorem applies: a formal isocontact immersions to \(N\) near a positive codimension subcomplex of \(M\) can be homotoped to a holonomic isocontact immersion on a \(C^0\)-slightly perturbed domain. In fact, the effect of the perturbation of the domain can be reversed by the contact isotopy extension theorem, using the observation that \(\mathcal{R}\) is invariant under the action of \(\mathrm{Cont}(M)\) on \(X^{(1)} = J^1(M, N)\).</p>

<p>Now suppose \(V\) is an arbitrary manifold, \((M, \xi_M)\) is a contact manifold, and</p>

\[(F, f) : (TV, V) \to (TM, M)\]

<p>is a formal Legendrian immersion. \(F\) maps \(TV\) fiberwise into \((\xi_M, \mathrm{CS}(\xi_M))\), therefore there is a canonical symplectic complement of \(F(TV)\) in \(f^*\xi\), isomorphic to \(T^*V\). Choosing a co-orientation for the distribution \(\xi\), we get a trivial line bundle complementary to \(\xi \subset TM\). Combining, we get that \(F(TV) \subset f^* TM\) has a complementary bundle isomorphic to \(T^*V \times \Bbb R\). This provides an extension of \((F, f)\) to a formal isocontact immersion \((\widehat{F}, \widehat{f}) : (T J^1V, J^1V) \to (TM, M)\). Applying the isocontact holonomic approximation theorem near the zero section as in the last paragraph, we obtain a holonomic Legendrian immersion \(\widetilde{f} : V \to M\) homotopic through formal Legendrian immersions to \((F, f)\) by a \(C^0\)-small homotopy. This finishes the proof.</p>

<p>In particular, this says any immersed path in \(\Bbb R^2\), no matter how complicated, can be approximated by bicycle trajectories. This is because any path in \(\Bbb R^2\) may be lifted to an immersion \(\Bbb R^2 \times S^1\) and upgraded to a formal Legendrian immersion, at which point one can use the result above. The projection of the Legendrian path back to \(\Bbb R^2\) (the “front projection”) need no longer be smooth, and in fact will contain many cusps: imagine the maneuvers needed to park a car in a tight space, and the track left by the process. In an appropriate sense, the holonomic approximation is possible precisely because of these zig-zags through cusps, which enable the tangent vectors to be parallel to the very twisty contact distribution.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="contact-topology" /><category term="h-principle" /><category term="symplectic-topology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Consider a bicycle on a 2-dimensional cartesian plane. We will choose coordinates \((x, y)\) for the position of the bicycle, and angle \(\theta\) that the steering wheel makes with the \(x\)-axis. In other words, our model of the bicycle has three degrees of freedom, two of them given by position in \(\Bbb R^2\) and the other given by the angle of the steering wheel in \(S^1\). Thus, the configuration space of the bicycle is \(M = \Bbb R^2 \times S^1\). The trajectory of such a bicycle in motion \(\gamma(t) = (x(t), y(t))\) on \(\Bbb R^2\) must have tangent \(\gamma'(t)\) parallel to the direction \((\cos \theta(t), \sin \theta(t))\) of the steering wheel. In other words, the motion of the bicycle is constrained by the differential relation \(\dot{x} \cos(\theta) - \dot{y} \sin(\theta) = 0\) on \(M\). The relation can be described as a rank 2 subbundle \(\xi \subset TM\) given by kernel \(\xi = \ker \alpha\) of a differential \(1\)-form \(\alpha = \cos(\theta) dx - \sin(\theta) dy\) on \(M\). Motions of trajectories of the bicycle are therefore paths \(\gamma\) in \(M\) which are parallel to the distribution \(\xi\), i.e., \(\gamma' \in \xi\).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seiberg-Witten Theory: IV</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/19/sw-theory-iv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seiberg-Witten Theory: IV" /><published>2022-03-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-03-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/19/sw-theory-iv</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/19/sw-theory-iv/"><![CDATA[<p>Let \(M\) be a closed oriented smooth \(4\)-manifold with a choice of a Riemannian metric \(g\), and a spinC-structure \(\mathfrak{s}\). The spinC-structure gives rise to a Clifford representation of the complexified tangent bundle \(\rho : T^{\Bbb C} M \to \mathrm{End}(S)\) on the complex spinor bundle \(S\) which is of rank \(4 = 2^{4/2}\), admitting a chiral decomposition \(S = S^- \oplus S^+\) and associated determinant line bundle \(L = \Lambda^2 S^+ \cong \Lambda^2 S^-\) whose 1st Chern class is the integral lift of the 2nd Stiefel-Whitney class of \(M\) coming from \(\mathfrak{s}\), as discussed in Part III. We choose a connection \(A\) on \(L\) which, combined with the LC connection on \((M, g)\), determines a spin connection on \(S\). Then there is an associated Dirac operator \(\slash \!\!\! \partial_A : \Gamma^{\pm}(S) \to \Gamma^{\mp}(S)\).</p>

<p>Moreover, we have the Hodge star operator \(\star : \Omega^2(M) \to \Omega^2(M)\) and we shall call the eigenspaces of \(\star\) of eigenvalues \(\pm 1\) as the self-dual and anti-self-dual \(2\)-forms, giving a decomposition \(\Omega^2 = \Omega^{2,+} \oplus \Omega^{2, -}\); we shall write \(\omega^+\) to mean the self-dual part of a \(2\)-form \(\omega\). The SD-ASD decomposition mirrors the chiral decomposition \(S = S^+ \oplus S^-\). More precisely, the connection between these is explained by the spin representation \(\rho : T^{\Bbb C} M \to \mathrm{End}(S) = S \otimes S\) which may be baked to a representation</p>

\[\displaystyle \rho : \Omega^2(M) \otimes \Bbb C = \Lambda^2 T^*M \otimes \Bbb C \to S \otimes S\]

<p>by replacing wedge with Clifford multiplication wherever it appears. We obtain the decomposition \(S^+ \otimes S^- \cong \Omega^0 \oplus \Omega^{2,+}\), a mnemonic for which is that a left-handed and a right-handed spin-1/2 fermion can combine to give a spin 0 (which has a single state, so rank of \(\Omega^0\) is \(1\)) or a spin 1 (which has three states -1, 0, 1, so rank of \(\Omega^{2,+}\) is \(3\)) fermion; note that the projection to the first factor is simply taking trace. Whenever \(\psi\) is a positive chirality spinor (a section of \(S^+\)), we will write \((\psi \otimes \psi^\dagger)_0\) to mean the trace-0 part of the tensor, conceptualized as a self-dual 2-form.</p>

<p>Given all of this, we shall now write down the Seiberg-Witten equations. For a pair \((A, \psi) \in \mathcal{A}(L) \oplus \Gamma(S^+)\), these are given by</p>

\[\displaystyle \slash \!\!\! \partial_A \psi = 0 \\ F_A^+ = (\psi \otimes \psi^\dagger)_0\]

<p>The second equation is the quadratic part; observe both sides are \(i \Bbb R\)-valued self-dual \(2\)-forms on \(M\). We may perturb the SW equations by adding \(i \mu\) to the right hand side of the second equation, for a fixed self-dual \(2\)-form \(\mu\), which I expect is useful for transversality arguments later.</p>

<p>The natural gauge symmetries of these equations is recorded by the group \(\mathcal{G} = C^\infty(M, S^1)\). For \(g \in \mathcal{G}\), it acts on the complex vector bundle \(S^+\) by pointwise multiplication; thus the induced action on sections is \(\psi \mapsto g \psi\) and the induced action on the line bundle \(L\) is by \(g^2\) (see Part III); this implies the action by conjugation on the covariant derivative \(\nabla^A_L\) corresponding to the connection \(A\) is given as follows:</p>

\[\displaystyle g^{-2} \nabla^A_L g^{2} = g^{-2} d g^{2} + g^{-2} A g^2 = -2g^{-1} dg + A\]

<p>Therefore, the induced action on connections is given by \(A \mapsto -2g^{-1} dg + A\). It is straightforward to check that SW-equations are invariant under the action of \(\mathcal{G}\); indeed \(\slash \!\!\! \partial_{g\cdot A} (g \cdot \psi) = \gamma^\mu ( g^{-1} \nabla^A_i g )g \psi = g^{-1} \gamma^\mu \nabla^A_i \psi\) and \(F_{g\cdot A}^+ = F_A^+\) as deforming the connection by a locally exact form \(-2g^{-1} dg = -2d\log(g)\) leaves the curvature invariant. The moduli space of solutions of the SW-equations, defined by the space of solutions modded out by the action of \(\mathcal{G}\) will be denoted as \(\mathcal{M}_{\mathfrak{s}, g, \mu}\).</p>

<p>The main result which will be discussed in the course of time is that \(\mathcal{M}_{\mathfrak{s}, g, \mu}\) is a compact, smooth, oriented manifold of dimension \(-(2\chi(M) + 3\sigma(M))/4 + c_1(L)^2\) for a generic perturbation \(\mu\) when \(b_2^+ &gt; 1\). In the zero dimensional case, counting the signed connected components gives us the so-called Seiberg-Witten invariants of \(M\).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="gauge-theory" /><category term="index-theory" /><category term="spin-geometry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let \(M\) be a closed oriented smooth \(4\)-manifold with a choice of a Riemannian metric \(g\), and a spinC-structure \(\mathfrak{s}\). The spinC-structure gives rise to a Clifford representation of the complexified tangent bundle \(\rho : T^{\Bbb C} M \to \mathrm{End}(S)\) on the complex spinor bundle \(S\) which is of rank \(4 = 2^{4/2}\), admitting a chiral decomposition \(S = S^- \oplus S^+\) and associated determinant line bundle \(L = \Lambda^2 S^+ \cong \Lambda^2 S^-\) whose 1st Chern class is the integral lift of the 2nd Stiefel-Whitney class of \(M\) coming from \(\mathfrak{s}\), as discussed in Part III. We choose a connection \(A\) on \(L\) which, combined with the LC connection on \((M, g)\), determines a spin connection on \(S\). Then there is an associated Dirac operator \(\slash \!\!\! \partial_A : \Gamma^{\pm}(S) \to \Gamma^{\mp}(S)\).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seiberg-Witten Theory: III</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/sw-theory-iii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seiberg-Witten Theory: III" /><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/sw-theory-iii</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/01/03/sw-theory-iii/"><![CDATA[<p>I will begin by discussing a little bit about my limited understanding of the origin of the Dirac operator, readers are welcome to point out the many errors that will follow.</p>

<p>A relativistic scalar field is a function \(\phi : \Bbb R^4 \to \Bbb C\) on space-time. The Lagrangian for a free scalar field of mass \(m &gt; 0\) is \(\mathcal{L} = (\eta^{\mu \nu} \partial_\mu \phi^* \partial_\nu \phi - m^2 \phi^*\phi)/2\) where \(\eta^{\mu \nu}\) denotes the Minkowski metric. This is supposed to mimic the Lagrangian for a simple harmonic oscillator, given as \(\mathcal{L} = (\dot{x}^2 - \omega^2 x^2)/2\); indeed, a common way to motivate the free scalar field is as a scaling limit of a lattice of harmonic oscillators across space-time, under the mesh of the lattice tending to \(0\). See <a href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/127141/in-what-sense-is-a-quantum-field-an-infinite-set-of-harmonic-oscillators">here</a> for an interesting discussion regarding the validity of such an interpretation. We compute the Euler-Lagrange equations:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\frac{\partial}{\partial x^\mu} \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \dot{\phi}_\mu} &amp;= \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \phi} \\ \frac{\partial}{\partial x^\mu} \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \dot{\phi}^*_\mu} &amp;= \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \phi^*}\end{aligned}\]

<p>which gives \((\Box + m^2)\phi = 0\) and \((\Box + m^2)\phi^* = 0\) where \(\Box = \eta^{\mu\nu} \partial^2_{\mu\nu} = \partial^2_t - \partial^2_x - \partial^2_y - \partial^2_z\) is the d’Alembert operator; this is known as the Klein-Gordon equation. The drawback of the setup of free scalar fields is that there is no obvious quantum mechanical interpretation; indeed, observe that the Lagrangian as a function of the generalized coordinates \(\phi, \phi^*, \partial_\mu \phi, \partial_\mu \phi^*\) is invariant under Lorentz transformations as \(\eta^{\mu \nu}\) is Lorentz-invariant; Noether’s theorem then gives rise to a conserved quantity which may be checked to be the 4-vector \(j^\mu = \phi^* \partial_\mu \phi - \phi \partial_\mu \phi^*\). The conservation can be explicitly checked by verifying \(\eta^{\mu \mu} \partial_\mu j^\mu = 0\). This is the probability current density; in QM the corresponding quantity has \(j^0\) as the probability density, but in this setup \(j^0 = \phi^* \partial_t \phi - \phi \partial_t \phi^*\) can be negative, since the Klein-Gordon equation is a second order PDE so the initial conditions \(\psi, \partial_\mu \psi\) at \(t = 0\) can be chosen arbitrarily.</p>

<p>This is one of the reasons Dirac wanted to figure out a first order PDE as the equation of motion. So he started by writing \((i \gamma^\mu \partial_\mu - m) \phi = 0\) where \(\gamma^0, \gamma^1, \gamma^2, \gamma^3\) are arbitrary “constants”. The equation must be compatible with the Klein-Gordon equation for free scalar field, so by multiplying the above equation with its conjugate:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}(i \gamma^\mu \partial_\mu + m)(i \gamma^\mu \partial_\mu - m) \phi &amp;= 0 \\ \implies (\gamma^{\mu} \gamma^{\nu} \partial^2_{\mu \nu} + m^2)\phi &amp;= 0\end{aligned}\]

<p>Comparing with the Klein-Gordon equation, we obtain the relations \(\gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu + \gamma^\nu \gamma^\mu = 2\eta^{\mu \nu}\). Astute readers will observe that these are exactly the Clifford relations where the underlying quadratic space is the Minkowski space \((\Bbb R^4, \eta^{\mu\nu})\), discussed in detail in the positive definite case in Part I and II. There is a completely analogous irreducible complex spinor representation of \(\mathrm{Cliff}_{1, 3}(\Bbb R)\) on \(S = \Bbb C^4\), for example using the gamma matrices</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\gamma^0 &amp;= \begin{pmatrix}1 &amp; &amp; &amp; \\ &amp; 1 &amp; &amp; \\ &amp; &amp; -1 &amp; \\ &amp; &amp; &amp; -1\end{pmatrix}, &amp;\gamma^1 = \begin{pmatrix} &amp; &amp; &amp; 1 \\ &amp; &amp; 1 &amp; \\ &amp; -1 &amp; &amp; \\ -1 &amp; &amp; &amp; \end{pmatrix}, \\ \gamma^2 &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} &amp; &amp; &amp; i \\ &amp; &amp; i &amp; \\ &amp; -i &amp; &amp; \\ -i &amp; &amp; &amp; \end{pmatrix}, &amp;\gamma^3 = \begin{pmatrix} &amp; &amp; 1 &amp; \\ &amp; &amp; &amp; -1 \\ -1 &amp; &amp; &amp; \\ &amp; 1 &amp; &amp; \end{pmatrix}\end{aligned}\]

<p>The operator \(\slash  \!\! \partial = \gamma^\mu \partial_\mu : C^\infty(\Bbb R^4) \otimes S \to C^\infty(\Bbb R^4) \otimes S\) is called the Dirac operator. Note that \(\slash \!\! \partial^2 = \Box\) is the square-root of the d’Alembertian. We can think of the domain and codomain \(C^\infty(\Bbb R^4) \otimes S \cong C^\infty(\Bbb R^4, S)\) as \(S\)-valued functions on spacetime or spinor fields. Thus, solutions to the Dirac operator are spinor fields \(\phi = (\phi^0, \phi^1, \phi^2, \phi^3) : \Bbb R^4 \to S\) and a basis of solutions can be extracted out: \(e^{-i m t} \mathbf{e}_1, e^{-i m t} \mathbf{e}_2, e^{i m t} \mathbf{e}_3, e^{i m t} \mathbf{e}_4\). These are independent of the spatial coordinates, so one can imagine these as the rest-solutions.</p>

<p>Let’s take some time to interpret what these four solutions mean. Observe that the complexified Lie algebra \(\mathfrak{spin}(1,3) \subset \mathrm{Cliff}(1, 3)\) sits inside the Clifford algebra spanned by the \(S_{ij} = \frac12 \gamma^i \gamma^j\) for \(i \neq j \in \{0, \cdots, 3\}\) which can be checked by exhibiting these as tangent vectors to an appropriate path starting at the identity, and observing that the dimension matches that of \(\Lambda^2 \Bbb R^4 \cong \mathfrak{so}(4)\) which is the same as \(\mathfrak{so}(1, 3)\) upon complexifying. The elements \(S_{01}, S_{02}, S_{03}\) are infinitisimal Lorentz boosts and \(S_{23}, S_{31}, S_{12}\) are the infinitisimal rotations, about the \(x, y, z\)-axes, respectively. Next, note that in the gamma matrix representation above, \(i S_{12}\) has eigenvectors \(\mathbf{e}_1, \mathbf{e}_3\) with eigenvalue \(1/2\) (“spin up” states) and eigenvectors \(\mathbf{e}_2, \mathbf{e}_4\) with eigenvalue \(-1/2\) (“spin down” states). What this says about the solutions above is that the first pair and the second pair of solutions are fields with different spins along the \(z\)-axis.</p>

<p>What does the fact that there are two pairs of spin up/down solutions mean? The point is the first pair solves for fermions at rest, whereas the second pair solves for antifermions at rest: mass is never negative, so \(e^{imt} = e^{-im(-t)}\) indicates that the time is negated, and moreover from the definition of relativistic 4-momentum, the energy \(E = -m\) is negated as well… that is, the second pair of solutions are predicting fields which quantize to particles travelling backward in time with negative energy. The Dirac equation, therefore, solves for massive fermionic/antifermionic spin-1/2 fields; whenever a massive fermionic particle appears in vacuum under a free field, they appear paired with an antifermion, and after generation of the pair they leave in opposite time-directions. Soon after Dirac posited this theoretical prediction of antiparticles, Carl D. Anderson experimentally verified the existence of positrons for which he was awarded the Nobel prize in the 30’s.</p>

<p>Remark 1: One way to organize this is using the chirality operator \(\gamma^5 := i \gamma^0 \gamma^1 \gamma^2 \gamma^3\) which is the volume element in the Clifford algebra. Observe that in the Dirac representation, \(\gamma^5\) simply switches the first two coordinates with the last two, i.e., the fermionic solutions go the antifermionic solutions and vice versa, as \((\gamma^5)^2 = 1\). The eigenspaces of \(\gamma^5\) corresponding to the eigenvalues \(\pm 1\) gives a chiral decomposition \(S = S^+ \oplus S^-\) of the spinor representation, as discussed in Part I and II. Moreover, note \(\{\gamma^5, \gamma^\mu\} = 0\), so \(\{\gamma^5, \slash  \!\!  \partial\} = 0\). In particular, \(\slash  \!\!  \partial\) flips the eigenspaces of \(\gamma^5\), i.e., \(\slash  \!\!  \partial(S^{\pm}) = S^{\mp}\).</p>

<p>As all good stories must come to an end, so will this one, and we shall move on to the most general context in which Dirac operator can be defined, a la Atiyah-Singer. Let \((M^n, g)\) be an even dimensional Riemannian manifold \(n = 2m\) with a spinC structure. It admits a complex spinor bundle \(S\) of rank \(2^m\) with spinor representation \(\rho : TM \to \mathrm{End}_{\Bbb C}(S)\) as described in Part II. Let \(\cdot\) denote the Clifford multiplication and \(\nabla\) denot the Levi-Civita connection on \((M, g)\).</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. A spin connection on \(M\) is a unitary connection \(\nabla^s\) on \(S\) such that</p>

\[\nabla^s_X(Y \cdot s) = (\nabla_X Y) \cdot s + Y \cdot \nabla^s_X(s)\]

<p>A brief explanation is imperative here. Given a manifold \(M\), a connection \(\nabla\) is a differential operator which eats two tangent vector fields \(X, Y\) and spits out a new tangent vector field \(\nabla_X Y\) such that \(\nabla\) is bilinear in either variables when taken linear combination with real constant scalars, but behaves in the following way under multiplication by scalar fields: \(\nabla_{f X} Y = f \nabla_X Y\), and \(\nabla_X (fY) = X(f) Y + f \nabla_X Y\). Therefore, such operators are global analogue of the directional derivative operator in \(\Bbb R^n\). There are many choices for a connection in general, but if \((M, g)\) is Riemannian there is a unique such operator which satisfies (1) torsion-freeness, i.e., \(\nabla_X Y - \nabla_Y X = [X, Y]\) and (2) metric-compatibility, i.e., \(X g(Y, Z) = g(\nabla_X Y, Z) + g(Y, \nabla_X Z)\); this is called a Levi-Civita connection. The fundamental theorem of Riemannian geometry says that such a connection is uniquely determined by the metric \(g\); the torsion-freeness condition might seem technical and unintuitive, but turn that perspective around and think of it as the right condition that makes the existence of a “good” connection an overdetermined problem, which gives this uniqueness.</p>

<p>An analogous story can be developed for a connection \(\nabla\) on a bundle \(E\) over \(M\), which eats a pair \((s, X)\) consisting of a section \(s \in \Gamma(M; E)\) (or an \(E\)-valued field) and a tangent vector field \(X\) on \(M\) and spits out a section \(\nabla_X(s) \in \Gamma(M; E)\) again. If \(E\) is a Hermitian bundle, then we can further demand an obvious metric-compatibility condition; we call such connections unitary. However, there is no analogue of the torsion-freeness condition as Lie brackets of \(E\)-valued fields are a nonsense concept, so there may be lots of unitary connections on a given bundle. We can measure the nonuniqueness explicitly; indeed, suppose \(\nabla, \nabla'\) are two different connections on \(E\). Then \(\nabla - \nabla'\) is an operator which is bilinear in both the tangent field variable and the \(E\)-field variable. Thus, for any tangent field \(X\) we can think of \(\nabla_X - \nabla'_X\) as an \(\mathrm{End}(E)\)-valued \(1\)-form on \(M\), i.e., \(\nabla - \nabla' \in \Omega^1(M; \mathrm{End}(E))\). This says that the space of connections \(\mathcal{A}_E\) on \(E\) is an affine space over the vector space \(\Omega^1(M; \mathrm{End}(E))\), in the sense that there is no preferred choice of origin. In local coordinates that trivialize the vector bundle, one can thus write any connection as \(\nabla = d + A\) where \(A\) is a matrix-valued \(1\)-form. Observe that the group \(\mathcal{G}_E := \mathrm{Aut}(E)\) of all self-automorphisms of the bundle (coordinate transformations of \(E\)-valued fields) acts on \(\mathcal{A}_E\) by conjugation \(A^g = dg A dg^{-1}\) (coordinate transformation acts on matrices by basechange); \(\mathcal{G}_E\) is called the gauge group and the space \(\mathcal{A}_E/\mathcal{G}_E\) is the moduli space of connections. This is a gigantic space; a better thing to do is to look at the moduli space of flat connections. More on this later.</p>

<p>Footnote: In general, one can define a connection on a bundle with a specified “structure group” that is a Lie group. For example, it is \(\mathrm{GL}(n, \Bbb R)\) for a real bundle, \(\mathrm{GL}(n, \Bbb C)\) for a complex bundle, \(\mathrm{O}(n)\) and \(\mathrm{SO}(n)\) for a bundle with a fiberwise metric that is unoriented or oriented respectively, \(U(n)\) for a Hermitian bundle as above, and \(\mathrm{Spin}(n)\) or \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) for a bundle with a real or complex spin structure. One can phrase these things better in terms of a “principal \(G\)-bundle”, and there is a dictionary between such objects and vector bundles with structure group in \(G\). In this case the connection is a \(\mathfrak{g}\)-valued object and the space of connections is an affine space over \(\Omega^1(M; \mathfrak{g})\), the space of \(\mathfrak{g}\)-valued \(1\)-forms on \(M\). A quick and clean introduction to these things is outside the scope of this post (but if you’re interested feel free to ask me!), and I’ll assume much of this below.</p>

<p>A spin connection entangles the horizontal/tangent vector fields with the vertical/spinor fields using the spinor representation of the former on the latter. Loosely speaking, the tangent vectors act on the spinors by gamma matrices, so one expects that, simply, \(\nabla^s_\nu(\gamma^\mu \sigma) = \gamma^\mu \nabla^s_\nu(\sigma)\). However, the catch here is that the gamma matrices change point-to-point since they are parametrized by the manifold, and the rate of change of \(\gamma^\mu\) in the \(\nu\)-direction is exactly \(\Gamma^{\kappa}_{\mu \nu} \gamma^{\kappa}\). So, the corrected formula is</p>

\[\nabla^s_\nu(\gamma^\mu \sigma) =\gamma^\mu \nabla^s_\nu(\sigma)  + \Gamma^\kappa_{\mu \nu} \gamma^{\kappa} \sigma\]

<p>Here is one approach to construct the spin connection using principal bundles: the LC connection \(\nabla\) on \(TM\) can be thought as an \(\mathfrak{so}(n)\)-valued connection \(\omega\) on the frame bundle of \(M\). Out of this, we want a \(\mathfrak{spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\)-valued connection on the spinC-frame bundle (see Part II) \(P\), at which point we can take the associated bundle \(P \times_{\rho_0} \Bbb C^{2^n}\) to recover the spinor bundle \(S\), and get an induced spin connection as well. To do this, observe \(\mathfrak{spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \cong \mathfrak{so}(n) \oplus i\Bbb R\). We shall define \(\slash  \!\!  \omega: M \to \mathfrak{spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) by defining it to be \(\omega\) in the first component and something else in the other component; this something else will be an arbitrarily chosen connection \(A\) on a complex line bundle; so jointly we shall define \(\slash  \!\!  \omega = (\omega, A)\). To construct such things, observe that the 2:1 map inducing isomorphism of Lie algebras \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \to \mathrm{SO}(n) \times S^1\) is \(\lambda q \mapsto (q, \lambda^2)\) where \(q\) denotes an even-degree monomial of unit norm and \(\lambda \in \Bbb C\) is a unit-norm complex scalar. The second projection is a character \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \to S^1\) given by \(\lambda^2\); using this we can obtain a complex line bundle \(\mathcal{L}\) out of a spinC structure as discussed in Part II. It follows from calculations in that post that then \(w_2(M) = c_1(\mathcal{L}) \pmod{2}\), so \(c_1(\mathcal{L})\) is the integral cohomology class lifting \(w_2(M)\); we take this to be our line bundle and choose a connection \(A\) on \(\mathcal{L}\). By construction, \(\tilde{\omega} = (\omega, A)\) defines a well-defined \(\mathfrak{spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\)-valued connection on the spinor bundle, and therefore a spin connection on \(S\).</p>

<p><em>Remark 2:</em> This story becomes much easier in dimension \(4\), essentially because there is a better way to understand the associated line bundle \(\mathcal{L}\): it’s just \(\Lambda^{top} S^+\), the determinant line bundle of the spinors of positive chirality. The reason that this is specific to dimension \(4\) is the simple but extremely amusing fact that \(n = 2^{n/2}\) for some \(n &gt; 2\) (think of one side as the number of spacetime coordinates and the other side as the number of spinor coordinates) iff \(n = 4\). I will explain this detail in an upcoming follow-up.</p>

<p><em>Remark 3:</em> What this shows is that given a spinor bundle \(S\) on a Riemannian manifold \((M, g)\), the spin connection \(\nabla^s\) depends on a choice of a connection \(A\) on the associated complex line bundle \(\mathcal{L}\) given by only thinking about the complex scalar spinors. This will be important later on as we discuss the Seiberg-Witten equations.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, now that we have a spinor bundle with a spin connection, we can write the Dirac operator, which is exactly the same expression as before, except we now use the spin connection and not the usual partial derivative:</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. In a local orthonormal frame \((\mathbf{e}^1, \cdots, \mathbf{e}^n)\) the Dirac operator is defined by</p>

\[\slash  \!\!  \partial_A = \gamma^\mu \nabla^s_\mu : \Gamma(M; S) \to \Gamma(M; S)\]

<p>where \(\gamma^\mu = \rho(\mathbf{e}^\mu)\) are images of the vectors under the spinor representation.</p>

<p>There’s a more coordinate-free way to say it: \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A\) is the composition of</p>

\[\nabla^s : \Gamma(M; S) \to \Gamma(M; S \otimes T^*M)\]

<p>followed by the isomorphism (Legendre transform)</p>

\[\Gamma(M; S \otimes T^*M) \to \Gamma(M; S \otimes TM)\]

<p>given by the Riemannian metric, further followed by the map</p>

\[\Gamma(M; S \otimes TM) \to \Gamma(M; S)\]

<p>given by the pointwise Clifford multiplication. It’s easy to see that the above expression is what this evaluates to in coordinates. Observe that by following the same argument as Remark 1, with the volume form as the chirality operator, we obtain \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A\) flips the decomposition \(S = S^+ \oplus S^-\) in the sense that \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A(S^\pm) = S^\mp\). We denote \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A^+ : \Gamma(M; S^+) \to \Gamma(M; S^-)\) and \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A^- : \Gamma(M; S^-) \to \Gamma(M; S^+)\) to be the restrictions of \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A\) to the positive and negative chirality spinors.</p>

<p>We will show that \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A\) is formally self-adjoint, equivalently, \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A^+\) is formally adjoint to \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A^-\). Suppose \(\sigma_1, \sigma_2 \in \Gamma_{supp}(M; S)\) be a pair of compactly supported sections of \(S\). Observe,</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\langle \slash  \!\!  \partial_A \sigma_1, \sigma_2 \rangle &amp;= \langle \gamma^\mu \nabla^s_\mu \sigma_1, \sigma_2 \rangle \\ &amp;= \langle \nabla^s_\mu \sigma_1, \gamma^\mu \sigma_2 \rangle \\ &amp;= -\langle \nabla^s_\mu \sigma_1, \gamma^\mu \sigma_2 \rangle \\ &amp;= - \partial_\mu \langle \sigma_1, \gamma^\mu \sigma_2 \rangle - \langle \sigma_1, \sigma_2 \nabla^s_\mu \gamma^\mu \rangle + \langle \sigma_1, \slash  \!\!  \partial_\mu \sigma_2 \rangle \end{aligned}\]

<p>Next, define a vector field \(X\) so that \(g(X, Y) = -\langle \sigma_1, \sigma_2 Y \rangle\) for all \(Y\). We compute the divergence:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}\mathrm{div}(X) = -\langle \nabla^s_\mu X, \gamma^\mu \rangle &amp;= -\partial_\mu \langle X, \gamma^\mu \rangle - \langle X, \nabla^s_\mu \gamma^\mu \rangle \\ &amp;= - \partial_\mu \langle \sigma_1, \sigma_2 \gamma^\mu \rangle - \langle \sigma_1, \sigma_2 \nabla^s_\mu \gamma^\mu \rangle \end{aligned}\]

<p>Combining, this shows \(\langle \slash  \!\!  \partial_A \sigma_1, \sigma_2 \rangle = \mathrm{div}(X) + \langle \sigma_1, \slash  \!\!  \partial_A \sigma_2 \rangle\). Integrating both sides over \(M\) and using divergence theorem, we obtain \(\slash  \!\!  \partial_A\) is self-adjoint with respect to the standard Hermitian inner product on compactly supported smooth sections of \(S\).</p>

<p>In the relativistic, flat spacetime, we had \(\slash  \!\!  \partial^2 = \Box\) is the d’Alembertian. In the nonrelativistic flat case we get \(\slash  \!\!  \partial^2 = \Delta\) where the Laplacian \(\Delta = - \partial_{\mu \mu}^2\) has an unfortunate negative sign in front of it because of my sign conventions. If spacetime has curvature, we choose coordinates such that \(\nabla^s_\mu \gamma^\nu(0) = 0\) and compute:</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned} \slash  \!\!  \partial^2 = \gamma^\mu \nabla^s_\mu (\gamma^\nu \nabla^s_\nu) &amp;= \gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu \nabla^s_\mu \nabla^s_\nu \\ &amp;= - (\nabla^s_\mu)^2 + \frac12 \gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu F_{\mu \nu}\end{aligned}\]

<p>Where \(F_{\mu \nu} = [\nabla^s_\mu, \nabla^s_\nu]\) is the curvature operator for the spin connection, and the first term is exactly the Laplacian. The connection \(1\)-form associated to the spin bundle is valued in \(\mathfrak{spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \cong \mathfrak{so}(n) \oplus i \Bbb R\), so \(\slash  \!\!  \omega = \omega + A\), which means \(F = R + F^A\) where \(R\) is the Riemann curvature tensor of \((M, g)\) and \(F^A\) is the curvature of the associated complex line bundle. Remembering \(\mathfrak{so}(n) \subset \mathfrak{spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) is spanned by \(1/2 \gamma^{\mu}\gamma^{\nu}\), we compute:</p>

\[\displaystyle \gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu R_{\mu \nu} = \frac14 R_{\mu \nu \sigma \rho} \gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu \gamma^\sigma \gamma^\rho\]

<p>We fix \(\rho\) and sum over the rest of the indices first. The terms where \(\mu, \nu, \sigma\) add up to \(0\) by Bianchi’s identity, so the result is \(R_{\mu \nu \mu \rho} \gamma^\nu \gamma^\rho\), and the terms where \(\nu, \rho\) are distinct also sum up in pairs and cancel, leaving \(2 R_{\mu \nu \mu \nu} (\gamma^\nu)^2 = -2 R_{\mu \nu \mu \nu} = 2\ \mathrm{scal}\). This gives</p>

\[\displaystyle \frac12 \gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu R_{\mu \nu} = \frac12 \cdot \frac14 \cdot 2 \ \mathrm{scal} = \frac{\mathrm{scal}}{4}\]

<p>Combining everything, we obtain the Weitzenböck formula:</p>

\[\displaystyle \slash  \!\!  \partial^2 \psi = \Delta \psi + \frac{\mathrm{scal}}{4} \psi + \frac{F^A}{2} \cdot \psi\]

<p>where \(F^A \cdot \psi = 1/2 F^A_{\mu \nu} \gamma^\mu \gamma^\nu \psi\) is the curvature of the line bundle acting by Clifford multiplication on spinor fields.</p>

<p>This concludes the basic discussion for the Dirac operator. Up next, we specialize to the case of dimension 4 and introduce the Seiberg-Witten equations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="clifford-algebras" /><category term="spin-geometry" /><category term="index-theory" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I will begin by discussing a little bit about my limited understanding of the origin of the Dirac operator, readers are welcome to point out the many errors that will follow.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seiberg-Witten Theory: II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/27/sw-theory-ii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seiberg-Witten Theory: II" /><published>2021-12-27T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-12-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/27/sw-theory-ii</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/27/sw-theory-ii/"><![CDATA[<p>Recall from the last paragraph of Part I that we wished to carry out all of the linear algebra but now parametrized over a manifold \(M\). Let us try to naively carry out the procedure, and in the process we will encounter the issue: let \((M, g)\) be a Riemannian \(n\)-manifold where \(n = 2m\) is even. The Riemannian metric \(g\) is a smoothly-varying inner product on each tangent space \(T_p M\), \(p \in M\) which assemble to the tangent bundle \(TM\), so one can take the Clifford algebra \(\mathrm{Cliff}(T_p M, g_p)\) for each \(p \in M\) and assemble these to a “Clifford algebra bundle” \(\mathrm{Cliff}(M) := \mathrm{Cliff}(TM, g)\). One can try to construct a fiberwise complex spinor representation, which would be a bundle \(S\) over \(M\) such that for each \(p \in M\), \(S_p\) is the complex spinor representation of \(\mathrm{Cliff}(T_pM, g_p)\); this we know how to construct, simply look at the complexification \(T_p^{\Bbb C} M := T_p M \otimes \Bbb C\) with the complexified inner product \(g^{\Bbb C}_p := g_p \otimes \Bbb C\) (which is a symmetric bilinear form, not a Hermitian inner product), take \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(T_p M, g_p) := \mathrm{Cliff}(T_p^{\Bbb C} M, g^{\Bbb C}_p)\) the complex Clifford algebra (which is in fact the complexification of the real Clifford algebra as described before in Part I) which assemble to the complex Clifford bundle \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(M)\), look at its action on the exterior algebra over the maximal totally isotropic subspace (or “Lagrangian subspace” in symplectic geometry terminology) of \(T_p^{\Bbb C} M\) as described previously, and that’s exactly \(S_p\). Assemble these up and we are done…</p>

<p>Except, to construct the maximal isotropic, we needed an extra piece of data, a choice of an orthogonal almost-complex structure or a transformation \(J_p  : T_p M \to T_p M\) such that \(J_p^2 = -I\) and \(J_p\) is an isometry with respect to \(g_p\); the eigenspace corresponding to the eigenvalue \(i\) of \(J_p\) on \(T_p^{\Bbb C} M\) is the maximal isotropic. This extra piece of data is not just a random choice that we can make; to assemble everything to a bundle at the end, we need a smoothly varying family of almost-complex structures on each tangent space of \(M\), i.e., a metric-compatible, fiberwise almost complex structure \(J : TM \to TM\), \(J^2 = -I\). Existence of such a thing is not automatic, in fact they do not always exist. Kahler manifolds (eg, smooth zero loci of homogeneous equations treated as subsets of \(\Bbb{CP}^n\)) are examples of such things, in fact they are exactly the ones for which this \(J\) is integrable in the sense that it gives rise to complex coordinate charts on the manifold; integrability is a closed condition \(J\) (the Nijenhuis tensor vanishes) so certainly Kahler manifolds are a rarer class than we are looking for. So what exactly are the Riemannian manifolds \((M, g)\) which admit an orthogonal almost-complex structure? Define \(\omega(X, Y) = g(X, JY)\) and observe that \(\omega\) is a \(2\)-form on \(M\), and moreover \(\omega^m := \omega \wedge \cdots \wedge \omega\) is a nowhere vanishing volume form on \(M\). Thus, \(\omega\) is an almost-symplectic structure, the difference from an actual symplectic structure being again an integrability condition: \(d\omega = 0\) or closedness of \(\omega\). On the other hand if \(M\) was an almost-symplectic manifold, the form \(\omega\) assumed to have no apriori compatibility with \(g\), one could have constructed an orthogonal almost-complex structure by the polar decomposition formula: \(J = (\Omega^{\mathsf{T}} \Omega)^{-1/2}\Omega\) where \(\Omega\) denotes the matrix of the bilinear form \(\omega\) with respect to some \(g\)-orthonormal basis; these are the so-called \(\omega\)-compatible almost complex structures (particularly relevant when \(\omega\) is symplectic, in the theory of pseudoholomorphic curves). In any case, we see that the class of manifolds we are interested in is larger, even, than symplectic manifolds.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, they are not abundant. The only spheres which admit an almost-complex structures are \(S^2\) and \(S^6\). Indeed, suppose \(TS^{2n}\) admits an almost complex structure \(J\). Then \(J \otimes \Bbb C\) gives an eigendecomposition of complex vector bundles \(T^{\Bbb C} S^{2n} = E \oplus \overline{E}\) where \(E = TS^{2n}\) with the complex structure \(J\), and \(\overline{E}\) is the conjugate. We compute the Chern class \(c_n\) of either side; note that \(c_n(T^{\Bbb C} S^{2n}) = 0\) by complex stable triviality of the complexified tangent bundle of the sphere, and \(c_n(E \oplus \overline{E}) = c_n(E) + c_n(\overline{E})\). If \(n\) was even, this would be \(2c_n(E) = 2\chi(S^{2n})[S^{2n}] = 4[S^{2n}]\), which gives the required contradiction. Note that the argument here is really a Pontryagin class argument, \(p_k(S^{4k}) = c_{2k}(T^{\Bbb C} S^{4k})\). Indeed, if \(k = 1\), then \(p_1(S^4) = 0\) can be seen geometrically, since by Chern-Weil theory \(p_1(M) = 1/(8\pi^2) \int_M \mathrm{tr}(\Omega^2)\) where \(\Omega\) is the curvature \(2\)-form of some chosen Riemannian metric on \(M\). If \(M\), like the sphere, admits a metric of constant curvature \(K\), then \(\Omega_{ij} = K d\omega^i \wedge d\omega^j\) which implies \(\Omega^2\) has no diagonal terms and so the \(1\)st Pontryagin form itself is zero. In the case \(n\) is odd, the above procedure gives no contradiction as \(c_n(\overline{E}) = -c_n(E)\); we can instead argue by Chern classes modulo \(p\) for some odd prime \(p\): from here, we see if \(n - p + 1 &gt; 0\), the universal Chern classes modulo \(p\), \(c_n \pmod{p}\) can be written as a polynomial in \(c_1 \pmod{p}, \cdots, c_{n-1} \pmod{p}\) and the first Steenrod power \(P^1(c_{n-p+1} \pmod{p})\). Specializing to \(TS^{2n}\) we get that since \(c_i = 0\) for all \(i &lt; n\), \(c_n(TS^{2n}) = 2[S^{2n}] \pmod{p} = 0\), which would be a contradiction. For this, we require an odd prime \(p\) such that \(p &lt; n - 1\), that is, \(n &gt; 4\). This leaves the cases \(n = 1, 2, 3, 4\) and \(n = 2, 4\) are eliminated by the earlier argument with the Pontryagin class. Thus, \(n = 1, 3\) are the only possibilities and these in fact do admit almost complex structure; whether \(S^6\) admits an integrable almost complex structure is still an open problem.</p>

<p>Here’s the punchline. You do not actually need an almost complex structure to get a spinor bundle, all you need is a much weaker spinc structure. My understanding is that the story of spin geometry begins with trying to “soften” almost complex geometry; almost complex structures are rare, so we would like to enlarge the tangent bundle to the “spinor bundle” where almost complex structures are abundant.</p>

<p>Let’s organize what we did in Part I from this viewpoint; given a real inner product space \((V, \langle \cdot, \cdot \rangle)\), we are interested in studying Clifford modules \(W\) over \(V\) which is a Hermitian inner product space \(W\) on which \(V\) acts in a way that each unit vector \(v \in V\) acts by an almost complex structure \(J_v : W \to W\), i.e., \(J_v^2 = -I\) and for any pair \(u, v \in V\) of unit vectors, \(J_u J_v = -J_v J_u\). That is to say, \(W\) is an enlargement of \(V\) which admit the unit sphere in \(V\)’s worth of almost-complex structures which are all compatible (i.e., for any pair of unit vectors \(u, v\), the complex structures \(I, J_u, J_v, J_u J_v\) form a linear almost-hyperKahler structure on \(W\)). The subalgebra of \(\mathrm{End}(W)\) generated by \(\{J_v : v \in V, \|v\| = 1\}\) is the (actual, physically perceivable) Clifford algebra \(\mathrm{Cliff}(V) \subset \mathrm{End}(W)\); one simply identifies \(v\) with \(J_v\) and composition of operators is the Clifford product, so \(V\) sits inside its Clifford algebra as the degree \(1\) elements. Next, observe that the axioms of the Clifford algebra implies for any pair of orthogonal unit vectors \(u, v\in V\), \(-vuv^{-1} = u\) unless \(u = \pm v\) in which case \(-vuv^{-1} = -u\). Define</p>

\[\begin{gather*}\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Cliff}(V)^\times \to \mathrm{End}(\mathrm{Cliff}(V)),\\
\mathrm{ad}_\alpha(u) = -\alpha u \alpha^{-1}\end{gather*}\]

<p>Observe that \(\mathrm{ad}_v(V) \subset V\) if \(v\) is a degree \(1\) element by our observation before. In fact, we get also from our observation that if \(\|v\| = 1\) then \(\mathrm{ad}_v\) is reflection along the hyperplane \(\langle v \rangle^\perp\). Thus, define,</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{align*}\mathrm{Pin}(V) &amp;= \{v_1 \cdots v_k \in \mathrm{Cliff}(V) : v_i \in V, \|v_i\| = 1\} \\ \mathrm{Spin}(V) &amp;= \mathrm{Pin}(V) \cap \mathrm{Cliff}^+(V)\end{align*}\]

<p>These are both subgroups of \(\mathrm{Cliff}(V)^\times\), and the adjoint representation restricts to homomorphisms (caveat: this doesn’t quite work, but the lie will be explained below) \(\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Pin}(V) \to \mathrm{O}(V)\) and \(\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Spin}(V) \to \mathrm{SO}(V)\) (here we are using that every orthogonal transformation is a product of reflections) which are \(2:1\) because \(\langle v \rangle^\perp = \langle -v\rangle^\perp\) so the reflections \(\mathrm{ad}_v\) and \(\mathrm{ad}_{-v}\) are the same. In fact they are both covering maps, and \(\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Spin}(V) \to \mathrm{SO}(V)\) is the universal cover.</p>

<p>There is an alternative description of these groups: consider the involution \(*\) on \(\mathrm{Cliff}(V)\) which acts on degree \(1\) elements by \(v^* := -\overline{v}\) and extending to monomials by reversing order: \((v_1 \cdots v_k)^* = v_k^* \cdots v_1^*\). The spinor norm is defined by \(\\|x\\| = x^* x\); observe on degree \(1\) elements this coincides with the norm coming from the inner product, and \(\\|xy\\| = \\|x\\| \\|y\\|\) follows from the definition. Thus, products of unit norm elements of \(V\) is contained in the unit sphere of \(\mathrm{Cliff}(V)\) under this norm, hence so is \(\mathrm{Pin}(V)\). But it is possible to have non-monomial elements in the unit sphere as well; to eliminate these we need the extra condition that \(x^* V x = V\). Indeed, then \(\mathrm{ad}_x \in \mathrm{O}(V)\) hence \(x \in \mathrm{Pin}(V)\) is forced. Therefore,</p>

\[\displaystyle \mathrm{Pin}(V) = \{x \in \mathrm{Cliff}(V) : \\|x\\| = 1, x^* V x = V\}\]

<p>and \(\mathrm{Spin}(V) = \mathrm{Pin}(V) \cap \mathrm{Cliff}^+(V)\) as before. Now we are in a position to explain the lie in the definition of the double cover \(\mathrm{Pin}(V) \to \mathrm{O}(V)\) above; the adjoint action \(\mathrm{ad}_x(u) = -xux^*\) is not a homomorphism in \(x\) from the full pin group. Indeed, \(\mathrm{ad}_x \circ \mathrm{ad}_{x'} = -\mathrm{ad}_{xx'}\); one has to correct for signs here, one of the many woes of working in a superalgebra. One way to do it is to taint an element with negative sign in odd degrees and positive sign in even degrees. Then \(\mathrm{ad}_x(v) := (-1)^{\|x\|} x v x^*\) works perfectly fine and agrees with the usual adjoint on the spin group, where sign is a non-issue as it lives in even degrees.</p>

<p>So far all we have talked about is the real Clifford algebra. The complex Clifford algebra is just obtained from tensoring everything up with \(\otimes_{\Bbb R} \Bbb C\); the last definition of the pin group goes through in this setup provided we complexify \(*\) correctly: define \(v^* = -\overline{v}\) in degree \(1\) instead; note that the conjugation only affects the scalars that hang around because of extending scalars to \(\Bbb C\) in the definition of the complex Clifford algebra, not the vectors themselves (remember the inner product on \(V \otimes \Bbb C\) is still a symmetric bilinear form, not a Hermitian one). We call the resulting groups \(\mathrm{Pin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) and \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\). Explicity,</p>

\[\displaystyle \begin{align*}\mathrm{Pin}^{\Bbb C}(V) &amp;= \{e^{i\theta} x \in \mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V) : x \in \mathrm{Pin}(V)\} \\
\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V) &amp;= \{e^{i\theta} x \in \mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V) : x \in \mathrm{Spin}(V)\}\end{align*}\]

<p>This time \(\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Pin}^{\Bbb C}(V) \to \mathrm{O}(V)\) and \(\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V) \to \mathrm{SO}(V)\) have kernel \(S^1 \cong U(1)\).  From the concrete description of the spin group above, we see \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) is almost \(U(1) \times \mathrm{Spin}(V)\), except \(\pm 1\) can appear in either factor, which leads to a \(\Bbb Z/2\)-ambiguity. Thus, \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V) \cong U(1) \times_{\Bbb Z/2} \mathrm{Spin}(V)\). As a consequence, \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) can also be thought as a double cover of \(U(1) \times \mathrm{SO}(V)\).</p>

<p>The real usage of complexifying everything up is that the representation theory of \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) is simpler than that of \(\mathrm{Cliff}(V)\). This is not strictly speaking relevant to us, but just to explain that comment I will go into a very brief detour: our focus has so far been on even-dimensional \(V\) but more or less everything discussed above goes through in odd-dimensions as well (however, \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) for odd dimensional \(V\) has two irreducible representations). Then for every \(n\) we have the Clifford algebras \(\mathrm{Cliff}(n)\) (what we called \(\mathrm{Cliff}_{n, 0}\) in Part I) and \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(n)\). But as it happens, there is a periodicity in the structure of these algebras: the complex Clifford algebras are \(2\)-periodic in the sense that \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(n+2) = M_2(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(n))\) whereas the real Clifford algebras happen to be \(8\)-periodic, i.e., \(\mathrm{Cliff}(n+8) = M_{16}(\mathrm{Cliff}(n))\). \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) is always either a matrix algebra (on its unique complex spinor representation) or a product of two matrix algebras (in case \(n\) is odd). But \(\mathrm{Cliff}(n)\) form the complicated Bott tower: the first eight algebras starting from \(n = 0\) are</p>

\[\displaystyle \Bbb R, \Bbb C, \Bbb H, \Bbb H \oplus \Bbb H, M_2(\Bbb H), M_4(\Bbb C), M_8(\Bbb R), M_8(\Bbb R) \oplus M_8(\Bbb R)\]

<p>One should conceptualize this as a linear version of the topological Bott periodicty, one of many ways of stating which is that the homotopy groups of \(O(\infty)\) are \(8\)-periodic.</p>

<p>Let me mention a modest, but illuminating example. \(\mathrm{Cliff}(3)\) is generated by \(e_1, e_2, e_3\), the full graded algebra breaks into four parts \(\mathrm{Cliff}_0 \oplus \mathrm{Cliff}_1 \oplus \mathrm{Cliff}_2 \oplus \mathrm{Cliff}_3\) indexed by degree. The degree \(2\) part is generated by \(e_1 e_2, e_2 e_3, e_3 e_1\) which can be sent to the quaternions \(i, j, k\); hence, there is an embedding \(\Bbb H \cong \mathrm{Cliff}(2) \hookrightarrow \mathrm{Cliff}(3)\) as the degree \(2\) elements (more generally, \(\mathrm{Cliff}(n-1)\) embeds in \(\mathrm{Cliff}(n)\) as the degree \(n-1\) elements). The degree \(0\) and \(3\) parts are both \(1\)-dimensional, the latter generated by \(e_1 e_2 e_3\). The \(\mathrm{Spin}(3)\) group lives inside the even degree part which is \(\mathrm{Cliff}_0 \oplus \mathrm{Cliff}_2 = \Bbb R \oplus i \Bbb H = \Bbb H\), consisting of all the elements of unit norm, i.e., \(\mathrm{Spin}(3) \cong S^3 \cong \mathrm{SU}(2)\). It is a classical fact that conjugation by a quaternion are rotations in the \(i\Bbb H\) factor, so this gives</p>

\[\mathrm{ad} : \mathrm{Spin}(3) \cong \mathrm{SU}(2) \to \mathrm{SO}(3)\]

<p>It is tempting to try to figure out \(\mathrm{Spin}(4)\) as well. From the Bott tower above we can see</p>

\[\mathrm{Cliff}(4) \cong \Bbb H \oplus \Bbb H\]

<p>This is in fact a \(*\)-algebra isomorphism. The unit sphere then is \(\mathrm{SU}(2) \times \mathrm{SU}(2)\). So, we have</p>

\[\mathrm{Spin}(4) \subseteq \mathrm{SU}(2) \times \mathrm{SU}(2)\]

<p>The equality holds as there is a \(2 : 1\) map \(\mathrm{SU}(2) \times \mathrm{SU}(2) \to \mathrm{SO}(4)\) given by \((q_1, q_2) \mapsto (u \mapsto q_1 u \overline{q_2})\), and the kernel is \(\Bbb Z/2 \cong \{(1, 1), (-1, -1)\}\). I haven’t quite worked out the details of how it fits together with the linear algebra of \(\mathrm{Cliff}(4)\), though.</p>

<p>The final piece of linear algebra that I want to discuss in this post is about how the complex Clifford algebra, the complex spinor representation and the spin group are tied together. First, observe (say, using Schur’s lemma) that \(\mathrm{End}_{\Bbb C}(S) \cong \mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V)\), so the Clifford algebra is completely recovered from the complex spinor representation. Next, consider the spinc automorphisms of \(S\), i.e., a pair of transformations \(A : V \to V\) and \(T : S \to S\) such that \(A\) is orthogonal and \(T\) is unitary, such that \(T \circ \rho \circ T^{-1} = \rho \circ A\) where \(\rho : V \to \mathrm{End}(S)\) is the (reified, i.e., in degree \(1\)) Clifford representation. Then we claim \(\mathrm{Aut}_{\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}}(S) \cong \mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\), so that the spin group is also recoverable from the complex spinor representation. Indeed, \(T \in \mathrm{End}(S) \cong \mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) hence \(T = \rho(x)\) for some \(x \in \mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V)\). Unitarity of \(T\) implies \(\\|x\\| = 1\); moreover the condition implies \(\rho(x^* v x) = \rho(A v)\) for all \(v \in V\). But \(\rho : \mathrm{Cliff}(V) \to \mathrm{End}(S)\) is an isomorphism so \(x^*vx = Av\). Therefore, \(\mathrm{ad}_x(V) = V\), but also \(\mathrm{ad}_x\) is an orientation-preserving transformation of \(V\). This implies \(x\) is in fact even, and so \(x \in \mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\), which proves the claim. Finally, the complex spinor representation itself can be restricted to the group \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V) \subset \mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) from the full Clifford algebra, which gives a representation, also called the complex spinor representation, \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V) \to \mathrm{End}(S)\). Recall in the case \(\dim V\) was even, we had defined a splitting \(S = S^+ \oplus S^-\) into the eigenspaces of the volume form on \(V\) and degree \(1\) elements acted on the decomposition by switching \(S^+, S^-\). As \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\) consists only even elements, we obtain that the representation over the spin group splits as \(S^+ \oplus S^-\); it is a fact that \(S^{\pm}\) are irreducible representations of \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(V)\).</p>

<p>Here is how all of this ties the topological setup that was being discussed in the first couple of paragraphs in the beginning of the post. Suppose that \(S\) is a spinor bundle over a Riemannian manifold \((M, g)\) of dimension \(n = 2m\). Consider the model spinc structure \(\rho_0 : \Bbb R^n \to \mathrm{End}(\Bbb C^{2^m})\) that was discussed in Part I. Then define a principal \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\)-bundle \(P_\rho \to M\) whose fiber over \(p \in M\) consists of all the spinc isomorphisms between \(\rho_0\) and \(\rho_p : T_p M \to \mathrm{End}(S_x)\); that is:</p>

\[\displaystyle P_\rho = \{(p, A, T) : A \in \mathrm{Isom}(\Bbb R^n, S_p), T \in \mathrm{Isom}(\Bbb C^{2^m}, S), T \circ \rho_0 \circ T^{-1} = \rho \circ A\}\]

<p>with \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) acting by \(\alpha \cdot (p, A, T) = (p, A \circ \mathrm{ad}_\alpha, T \circ \rho_0(\alpha))\). If we forget the factor of \(T\) then this is simply the orthonormal frame bundle \(\mathrm{Fr}(M) \to M\), fiber of a generic point \(p\) of which is simply the space of all possible frames of \(T_p M\), and \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) acts non-effectively by the projection \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \to \mathrm{SO}(n)\) to the group of orthogonal transformations, which simply permute the frames around over any given point. Remembering the spinor representation in the definition has the effect that the “spin” (whatever that is, more on this below) of the framing is remembered. In fact, consider \(P_\rho \times_{\mathrm{ad}} \mathrm{SO}(n) = (P \times  \mathrm{SO}(n))/\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) where \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) acts diagonally, on \(P\) by permuting the spin framings and on \(\Bbb R^n\) by \(\mathrm{ad}\). Then it is clear that \(P_\rho \times_{\mathrm{ad}} \mathrm{SO}(n) \cong \mathrm{Fr}(M)\), as one is collapsing down the \(T\) factor (“spin”) wherever they record more information than the \(A\) factor (“frames”), so one just ends up with the frames. This is an incredibly concise way of putting the idea of spinor bundles, and it is clear with a little though that one can go the other way as well; if there was a \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\)-equivariant map \(P \to \mathrm{Fr}(M)\) from some principal \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\)-bundle to the frame bundle, one could take \(P \times_{\rho_0} \Bbb{C}^{2^m}\) to get back the spinor representation, where \(\rho_0 : \mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \to M_{2^m}(\Bbb C)\) is the restriction of the model spinor representation to the spinc subgroup. All of this goes through likewise for real spinor representations as well, and parity of dimension of \(M\) is a mere convenience.</p>

<p><b>Definition</b>. A spinc structure on an oriented Riemannian manifold \((M^n, g)\) is a principal \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\)-bundle \(P \to M\) such that \(P \times_{\mathrm{ad}} \mathrm{SO}(n) \cong \mathrm{Fr}(M)\). Likewise, a spin structure is a principal \(\mathrm{Spin}(n)\)-bundle \(P \to M\) such that \(P \times_{\mathrm{ad}} \mathrm{SO}(n) \cong \mathrm{Fr}(M)\).</p>

<p>We have proved that admitting a (complex) spinor representation is equivalent to admitting a spinc structure. I will demonstrate that this is far, far more flexible a condition than admitting an almost complex structure, but before that I would like to present some pictures which puts it in an intuitive and handwavy way; after all, for much of the time we have been doing abstract linear algebra and it might seem at first that spin structures emerge out of playing such algebraic games. I would like to argue, on the contrary, that it “actually exists”  and something whose presence “can be felt”.</p>

<p>Let me discuss the real spin structure. Recall \(\mathrm{Spin}(n)\) is the universal double cover of \(\mathrm{SO}(n)\). For any nice topological group \(G\) the universal cover can be written as follows:</p>

\[\widetilde{G} = \{\gamma \in \mathrm{Maps}([0, 1], G) : \gamma(0) = e\}/\sim\]

<p>where \(\sim\) denotes homotopy relative to the basepoint \(0\). The covering projection \(\widetilde{G} \to G\) is \(\gamma \mapsto \gamma(1)\). Now, there is a group structure on \(\widetilde{G}\) which is given by \((\alpha \beta)(t) = \alpha(t) \beta(t)\) and this is the one which lifts the group structure on \(G\). However, it is equivalent to the group structure given by \(\alpha * (\alpha(1)\beta)\) where \(*\) denotes path concatenation, as can be seen by hand. Specialize to the case \(G = \mathrm{SO}(n)\), which tells you elements of \(\mathrm{Spin}(n)\) are paths in \(\mathrm{SO}(n)\) starting at the identity, with multiplication of two such paths given by translating the initial point to the endpoint of the other, and then concatenating.</p>

<p>To visualize this with \(n = 3\), consider the following artifice. Consider a sphere \(S^2 \subset \Bbb R^3\) with an infinite strip (or a framed, proper ray) attached to it, which has red markings by arrows pointing up:</p>

<div class="figure-row">
    <img src="/assets/images/belt-trick-1.webp" height="50%" width="50%" />
</div>

<p>\(\mathrm{SO}(3)\) acts on the sphere by rotating it, but when we physically carry out a rotation we will have to follow a path of rotations starting at the identity and leading to the required rotation; the purpose of the strip is to keep track of this path “in space” rather than “in time”. For example, this is the effect of rotating the sphere by \(2\pi\) around the blue axis, which is the identity operation but as the strip tells you, that path you traced out is a nontrivial loop in \(\mathrm{SO}(3)\).</p>

<div class="figure-row">
    <img src="/assets/images/belt-trick-2.webp" height="55%" width="55%" />
</div>

<p>Indeed, try to unravel the strip out by moving it to one side as it was before, and one ends up with the following configuration:</p>

<div class="figure-row">
    <img src="/assets/images/belt-trick-3.webp" height="55%" width="55%" />
</div>

<p>We see one of the red arrows pointing down, in other words a full twist in the strip. If we do it again, we might see either two full twists or none, depending on how we unravel the strip and bring it to one side - I encourage carrying this out by cutting out some paper strips. Therefore, it makes sense to count the number of twists on the strip modulo 2, i.e., the strip can have only two states, an “up” state and a “down” state, corresponding to any state of the sphere. This is exactly how elements of \(\mathrm{Spin}(3)\) look like. This description of the spin group is not new; it is called the Dirac’s belt/plate trick. An elaborate animation can be found <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f7/Anti-Twister.gif">here</a> where many such strips or belts are emerging out of the object that is exhibiting rotation.</p>

<p>I think of a spin structure on a manifold \(M\) as a collection of such strips or framed proper rays from infinity attached to each unit tangent sphere so that the manifold looks like a marionette, and the associated “spin field” is the signed count of the number of full-twists or the up/down states along the strings. Probably not very useful, but sort of pleasant.</p>

<p>Finally, let us get to exactly what kind of topological obstructions there are for a spin or spinc structure on a manifold to exist. Off the top of my head, here is a way to do this by throwing the kitchen sink at it: the frame bundle of \(M\) is classified by a map \(M \to B\mathrm{SO}(n)\), and the question of admitting a spin or spinc structure is the same question as lifting this to a map \(\psi : M \to B\mathrm{Spin}(n)\) or \(M \to B\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) respectively. In the first case, there is a fibration sequence \(\mathrm{SO}(n) \to \mathrm{Spin}(n) \to B\Bbb Z/2\) where the last map classifies the first map, which is a double covering. By delooping everything, we get a fibration sequence \(B\mathrm{SO}(n) \to B\mathrm{Spin}(n) \to B^2\Bbb Z/2\). Thus, the question of lifting a map from \(M\) to the middle term to a map into the fiber is equivalent to the question of whether the composition \(M \to B^2 \Bbb Z/2\) to the base is nullhomotopic. This is classified by an element of \(H^2(M; \Bbb Z/2)\); moreover it follows that this element lies in the image of the homomorphism \(\psi^* : H^2(B\mathrm{SO}(n); \Bbb Z/2) \to H^2(M; \Bbb Z/2)\). As explained in this post, the cohomology ring \(H^*(B\mathrm{SO}(n); \Bbb F_2) = \Bbb F_2[w_1, w_2, \cdots, w_n]\) is generated by universal Stiefel-Whitney classes, hence the unique nonzero element in degree \(2\) is \(w_2\). Thus, the class in \(H^2(M; \Bbb Z/2)\) is the second Stiefel-Whitney class \(w_2(M)\). In the second case, there is a fibration sequence \(\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \to \mathrm{SO}(n) \to BU(1)\) which one can deloop as before and argue that the relevant obstruction for lifting \(\psi\) to \(M \to B\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)\) lies in \(H^3(M; \Bbb Z)\). Apparently, the class here is the “3rd integral Stiefel-Whitney class” \(W_3 := \beta w_2\), where \(\beta : H^2(-; \Bbb F_2) \to H^3(-; \Bbb Z)\) is the integral Bockstein in degree \(2\), which looks intuitive enough but I haven’t worked out precisely why. Moreover, it might be worth phrasing all of this in terms of explicit cocycles than abstract obstruction theory.</p>

<p>Edit: I have figured out why the obstruction class is \(W_3 = \beta w_2\). There is a short exact sequence</p>

\[0 \to \Bbb Z/2 \to \mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n) \to \mathrm{SO}(n) \times \mathrm{U}(1) \to 0\]

<p>which is classified by an element of \(H^2(\mathrm{SO}(n) \times \mathrm{U}(1); \Bbb Z/2) \cong H^2(\mathrm{SO}(n); \Bbb Z/2) \oplus H^2(\mathrm{U}(1); \Bbb Z/2)\) whose projection to the first factor classifies the short exact sequence</p>

\[0 \to \Bbb Z/2 \to \mathrm{Spin}(n) \stackrel{\mathrm{ad}}{\to} \mathrm{SO}(n) \to 0\]

<p>obtained from the above short exact sequence by “forgetting the complex scalars” and the projection to the second factor classifies the short exact sequence</p>

\[0 \to \Bbb Z/2 \to U(1) \stackrel{\times 2}{\to} U(1)\]

<p>obtained from the same short exact sequence by “forgetting the orthogonal matrices”. Therefore, the pertaining element of \(H^2(\mathrm{SO}(n); \Bbb Z/2)\) is \(w_2\) and let us call the element in \(H^2(U(1); \Bbb Z/2)\) as \(\alpha\). Thus, the classifying element is \(w_1 + \alpha\). Extending the short exact sequence to a fiber long exact sequence by delooping and dualizing gives for any \(X\) a short exact sequence</p>

\[\displaystyle [X, B\mathrm{Spin}^{\Bbb C}(n)] \to [X, B\mathrm{SO}(n)] \oplus [X, B\mathrm{U}(1)] \to [X, B^2 \Bbb Z/2] \cong H^2(X; \Bbb Z/2)\]

<p>where the last map is, treating \([X, BG]\) as the group of isomorphism classes of principal \(G\)-bundles,</p>

\[(E, F) \mapsto w_2(E) + \alpha(F) \pmod{2}\]

<p>Thus, \(E\) is a spinc-bundle if and only if \((E, E)\) maps to \(0\) if and only if</p>

\[w_2(E) = \alpha(E) \pmod{2}\]

<p>Observe this condition is equivalent to demanding that \(\alpha(E)\) is an integral lift in \(H^2(X; \Bbb Z)\) of \(w_2(E) \in H^2(X; \Bbb Z/2)\). Thus, \(\beta w_2(E) = 0 \in H^3(X; \Bbb Z)\) by construction of Bockstein. In fact, once \(E\) has a spinc-structure then one focus on the complex scalars in the structure group and immediately turn it into a complex bundle, and \(c_1(E) = \alpha(E)\) is exactly its first Chern class.</p>

<p>In either case, it is evident from this that the existence of spin or spinc structures is much easier than almost complex structures; to start, all spheres have them! Every oriented \(3\)-manifold admits a spin structure because they are parallelizable, so all the pertaining characteristic classes vanish. Apparently, it is true that any oriented \(4\)-manifold admits a spinc structure.</p>

<p>Next time, we shall discuss some geometry: the spin connection and the Dirac operator.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="characteristic-classes" /><category term="clifford-algebras" /><category term="representation-theory" /><category term="spin-geometry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recall from the last paragraph of Part I that we wished to carry out all of the linear algebra but now parametrized over a manifold \(M\). Let us try to naively carry out the procedure, and in the process we will encounter the issue: let \((M, g)\) be a Riemannian \(n\)-manifold where \(n = 2m\) is even. The Riemannian metric \(g\) is a smoothly-varying inner product on each tangent space \(T_p M\), \(p \in M\) which assemble to the tangent bundle \(TM\), so one can take the Clifford algebra \(\mathrm{Cliff}(T_p M, g_p)\) for each \(p \in M\) and assemble these to a “Clifford algebra bundle” \(\mathrm{Cliff}(M) := \mathrm{Cliff}(TM, g)\). One can try to construct a fiberwise complex spinor representation, which would be a bundle \(S\) over \(M\) such that for each \(p \in M\), \(S_p\) is the complex spinor representation of \(\mathrm{Cliff}(T_pM, g_p)\); this we know how to construct, simply look at the complexification \(T_p^{\Bbb C} M := T_p M \otimes \Bbb C\) with the complexified inner product \(g^{\Bbb C}_p := g_p \otimes \Bbb C\) (which is a symmetric bilinear form, not a Hermitian inner product), take \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(T_p M, g_p) := \mathrm{Cliff}(T_p^{\Bbb C} M, g^{\Bbb C}_p)\) the complex Clifford algebra (which is in fact the complexification of the real Clifford algebra as described before in Part I) which assemble to the complex Clifford bundle \(\mathrm{Cliff}^{\Bbb C}(M)\), look at its action on the exterior algebra over the maximal totally isotropic subspace (or “Lagrangian subspace” in symplectic geometry terminology) of \(T_p^{\Bbb C} M\) as described previously, and that’s exactly \(S_p\). Assemble these up and we are done…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Steenrod Squares</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/26/steenrod-squares/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Steenrod Squares" /><published>2021-12-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-12-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/26/steenrod-squares</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/26/steenrod-squares/"><![CDATA[<p>These are some roughly written notes I am preparing as I study Steenrod operations. I expect nothing new beyond what is in Hatcher Chapter 4.L will be said here, but I will mention other references if I use them. This post is not going to be part of a series, and will instead be updated as I progress and decide to write more.</p>

<p>A cohomology operation of type \((G_1, G_2, m_1, m_2)\) is a natural transformation</p>

\[H^{m_1}(-; G_1) \to H^{m_2}(-; G_2)\]

<p>where \(H^*\) denotes singular cohomology. In other words, they are homomorphisms</p>

\[\Phi_X : H^{m_1}(X; G_1) \to H^{m_2}(X; G_2)\]

<p>such that for any map \(f : X \to Y\), \(f^* \Phi_Y(\alpha) = \Phi_X(f^* \alpha)\); we will mostly drop the reference to the space \(X\) and denote the natural transformation by \(\Phi\), as the space will be clear from context. One way to understand the motivation here is via the fact that singular cohomology is representable by Eilenberg-Maclane space \(K(G, n)\) (recall these are CW-complexes characterized uniquely upto homotopy equivalence by the property that all the homotopy groups vanish except the one in degree \(n\), and \(\pi_n \cong G\)), that is, \(H^n(X; G) = [X, K(G, n)]\) where \([A, B]\) denotes based homotopy classes of maps \(A \to B\). Therefore, invoking Yoneda’s lemma, we obtain that cohomology operations of type \((G_1, G_2, m_1, m_2)\) are classified by elements of \(H^{m_2}(K(G_1, m_1); G_2)\). As a corollary, nontrivial cohomology operations only exist when \(m_1 \leq m_2\). Moreover if \(m_1 = m_2\) then by Hurewicz’s theorem and universal coefficients theorem, we compute the cohomology group to be \(\mathrm{Hom}(G_1, G_2)\), which implies the only cohomology operations in this case are change-of-coefficients homomorphisms. First interesting examples of cohomology operations are \(H^k(X; \Bbb F_p) \to H^{kp}(X; \Bbb F_p)\) given by \(\alpha \mapsto \alpha^p\).</p>

<p>In the case \(p = 2\), the cup-square modulo 2 is a useful cohomology operation and can be used to detect topology. For example, consider \(\Bbb{CP}^2\) and \(S^2 \vee S^4\). These spaces have the same cohomology groups by cellular homology. However, if \(\alpha \in H^2(\Bbb{CP}^2; \Bbb F_2)\) denotes the generator then \(\alpha^2 = 1\) but there is no degree \(2\) element in the cohomology ring of \(S^2 \vee S^4\) which squares to \(0\); incidentally this says the attaching map of the \(4\)-cell in \(\Bbb{CP}^2\), which is the Hopf map \(h : S^3 \cong \partial D^4 \to (\Bbb{CP}^2)^{(3)} = S^2\), is not nullhomotopic, implying \(\pi_3(S^2) \neq 0\). The major drawback with this operation, though, is that it is not stable under suspension. Indeed, the ring structure in \(H^*(\Sigma \Bbb{CP}^2; \Bbb F_2)\) is completely trivial, cup product of any pair of elements is \(0\). However, \(\Sigma \Bbb{CP}^2\) is not homotopy equivalent to \(\Sigma(S^2 \vee S^4) \simeq S^3 \vee S^5\). To prove something like this, we need to develop a stable generalization of the cup-square modulo 2 or the \(p\)-th power operation modulo \(p\) in general; these are exactly what Steenrod squares or Steenrod power operations are, respectively. Notice that as a corollary of this we end up proving that the attaching map of the \(5\)-cell in \(\Sigma \Bbb{CP}^2\), which is the suspension \(\Sigma h : S^4 \to S^3\) of the Hopf map is not nullhomotopic, which demonstrates \(\pi_4(S^3) \neq 0\). Indeed, we shall end up proving that the spaces are never homotopy equivalent even if they are suspended \(k\)-fold, which demonstrates the first stable stem \(\pi_1^s := \lim_k \pi_{k+1}(S^k) \neq 0\). (Actually, one can deduce this from just \(\pi_4(S^3) \neq 0\), by the sharp version of the Freudenthal suspension theorem specifying the stable range.)</p>

<p>There are two cases to consider, \(p = 2\) and \(p\) an odd prime. In the former, we shall have the Steenrod square operations \(Sq^i : H^n(X; \Bbb F_2) \to H^{n+i}(X; \Bbb F_2)\) for every \(i \geq 0\). In the latter case, we shall have the Steenrod power operations \(P^i : H^n(X; \Bbb F_p) \to H^{n+2i(p-1)}(X; \Bbb F_p)\) for every \(i \geq 0\). These operations are characterized by the following axioms:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>\(Sq^0 = \mathbf{1}, P^0 = \mathbf{1}\).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>\(Sq^1 = \beta_2\) is the Bockstein homomorphism for the sequence \(0 \to \Bbb Z_2 \to \Bbb Z_4 \to \Bbb Z_2 \to 0\).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>\(Sq^i a = a^2\) if \(i = \vert a\vert\), \(Sq^i a = 0\) if \(i &gt; \vert a\vert\), and likewise \(P^i a = a^p\) if \(2i = \vert a\vert\), \(P^i a = 0\) if \(2i &gt; \vert a\vert\).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>\(Sq^i \sigma = \sigma Sq^i, P^i \sigma = \sigma P^i\), where \(\sigma : H^*(X) \to H^*(\Sigma X)\) is the suspension isomorphism.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Cartan’s formula: \(Sq^j(a \smile b) = \sum_i Sq^i a\smile Sq^{j-i} b\) and \(P^j(a \smile b) = \sum_i P^i a \smile P^{j-i} b\).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Adem relations regarding compositions of Steenrod squares or powers:</p>
  </li>
</ol>

\[\displaystyle \begin{aligned}Sq^i Sq^j &amp;= \sum_k \binom{j-k-1}{i-2k} Sq^{i+j-k} Sq^k, \; i &lt; 2j \\ P^i P^j &amp;= \sum_k (-1)^{i+k} \binom{(p-1)(j-k)-1}{i-pk} P^{i+j-2k} P^k, \; i &lt; pj \\ P^i \beta_p P^j &amp;= \sum_k (-1)^{i+k} \binom{(p-1)(j-k)-1}{i-pk} \beta_p P^{i+j-k} P^k \\ &amp;- \sum_k (-1)^{i+k} \binom{(p-1)(j-k)-1}{i-pk-1} P^{i+j-k} \beta_p P^k, \; i \leq pj.\end{aligned}\]

<p>Define the totals \(Sq : H^*(X; \Bbb F_2) \to H^*(X; \Bbb F_2)\) and \(P : H^*(X; \Bbb F_p) \to H^*(X; \Bbb F_p)\) as</p>

\[\begin{align*} Sq &amp;= Sq^0 + Sq^1 + Sq^2 + \cdots \\ P &amp;= P^0 + P^1 + P^2 + \cdots\end{align*}\]

<p>Then Cartan’s formula is just stating \(Sq\) and \(P\) are ring endomorphisms. The relativized versions \(Sq : H^*(X, A; \Bbb F_2) \to H^*(X, A; \Bbb F_2)\) and \(P : H^*(X, A; \Bbb F_p) \to H^*(X, A; \Bbb F_p)\) of the operations can be constructed from the axioms via the natural isomorphism \(H^*(X, A) \cong H^*(X/A)\); for these we require the Cartan formula is true under relative cup product \(H^*(X, A) \times H^*(X, B) \to H^*(X, A \cup B)\). The axioms above are not independent in any sense. In fact, the rest of the axioms follow from the relativized versions of 1, 3 and 5 (see Epstein-Steenrod)</p>

<p>We begin with the construction of the Steenrod squares and power operations instead. The general idea is pretty geometric: consider the \(p\)-fold exterior cup product</p>

\[H^*(X; \Bbb F_p)^{\otimes p} \to H^*(X^p; \Bbb F_p)\]

<p>Let \(\alpha \in H^n(X; \Bbb F_p)\) be an element, and consider its image under the map \(\alpha^{\otimes p}\). Appealing to the fact quoted in the first paragraph of this post, this is represented by a map \(f : X^p \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\). Note that \(\Bbb Z/p\Bbb Z\) acts on \(X^p\) by permuting the factors cyclically. Let us define</p>

\[\begin{gather*}T : X^p \to X^p \\ T(x_1, \cdots, x_p) = (x_p, x_1, \cdots, x_{p-1})\end{gather*}\]

<p>Then $T$ generates the aforementioned cyclic action. The composition \(f \circ T : X^p \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\) is a new map but it is nonetheless homotopic to the older map \(f\) as they both represent the same element \(\alpha^{\otimes p} \in H^{np}(X^p; \Bbb F_p)\). The homotopy can be written as a map \(X^p \times [0, 1/p] \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\) (the odd choice \([0, 1/p]\) for the time-interval will be clear in a bit). One can argue the same for \(f \circ T\) and \(f \circ T^2\) and obtain a homotopy \(X^p \times [1/p, 2/p] \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\), and so on until we have come back full circles to \(f \circ T^{p-1}\) and \(f \circ T^p = f\). Paste these homotopies end-to-end to get a map</p>

\[f_1 : X^p \times S^1 \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\]

<p>It turns out that one can choose all the earlier homotopies between \(f, f \circ T, f \circ T^2, \cdots\) carefully such that, by obstruction theory, \(f_1\) is nullhomotopic. Once that is established, consider the \(\Bbb Z/p\)-action on \(X^p \times S^1\) given by a diagonal action where the action on \(X^p\) is as before and on \(S^1\) is given by a \(2\pi/p\) rotation, permuting the arcs which were intervals of the earlier homotopies; these \(\Bbb Z/p\)-translates of \(f_1\) are also all nullhomotopic, and the nullhomotopies \(X^p \times D^2 \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\) glue up to a map</p>

\[f_2 : X^p \times E_2 \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np),\]

<p>where \(E_2\) is the complex given by attaching \(p\)-many \(2\)-cells to the circle, and it admits a \(\Bbb Z/p\)-action which simultaneously rotates the “equator” \(S^1\) by \(2\pi/p\) and cyclically permutes the \(2\)-cells. Inducting upward, one ends up with a map \(f_\infty : X^p \times E\Bbb Z/p \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\) where \(E\Bbb Z/p\) is a contractible complex on which \(\Bbb Z/p\) acts freely. Restrict this map on the first factor to the diagonal copy of \(X \subset X^p\), and mod out by the \(\Bbb Z/p\)-action to get a map \(X \times B\Bbb Z/p \to K(\Bbb Z/p, np)\). This represents an element in</p>

\[H^{*}(X \times B\Bbb Z/p; \Bbb F_p) \cong H^{*}(X; \Bbb F_p) \otimes \Lambda_{\Bbb F_p}^*[x] \otimes \Bbb F_p[y]\]

<p>of degree \(np\), where \(\vert x\vert  = 1, \vert y\vert  = 2\). Therefore, the element can be written as</p>

\[\sum_{0 \leq i \leq np} \omega_{(p-1)n-i} \otimes \theta_i(\alpha)\]

<p>where \(\omega_{2j} = y^j, \omega_{2j+1} = x y^j\) and \(\theta_i(\alpha) \in H^{n+i}(X; \Bbb F_p)\). If \(p = 2\), the Steenrod squares will be \(Sq^i = \theta_i\) and if \(p\) is an odd prime the Steenrod powers will be \(P^i = \kappa_i \theta_{2i(p-1)}\) for certain appropriate normalizing factor \(\kappa_i\).</p>

<p><em>Caveat</em>: Here we used the isomorphism</p>

\[H^*(B\Bbb Z/p; \Bbb F_p) \cong \Lambda^*_{\Bbb F_p}[x] \otimes \Bbb F_p[y],\]

<p>where \(\vert x\vert  = 1, \vert y\vert  = 2\). To demonstrate this, observe \(B\Bbb Z/p\) is an infinite dimensional lens space so has a single cell in every dimension; the integral cellular cochain complex has differentials alternating between \(0\) and multiplication by \(p\) whereas the mod \(p\) cellular cochain complex has no differentials. By naturality with respect to the change of coefficients homomorphism \(\Bbb Z \to \Bbb Z_p\), we see that the map from integral cohomology is surjective in even degrees and zero in odd degrees. Comparing the Bockstein sequences corresponding to the short exact sequences \(0 \to \Bbb Z \to \Bbb Z \to \Bbb Z_p \to 0\) and \(0 \to \Bbb Z_p \to \Bbb Z_{p^2} \to \Bbb Z_p \to 0\), we obtain that the Bockstein homomorphism</p>

\[\beta_p : H^n(B\Bbb Z/p; \Bbb F_p) \to H^{n+1}(B\Bbb Z/p; \Bbb F_p)\]

<p>is zero in even degrees and an isomorphism in odd degrees. Next, let \(y \in H^2(B \Bbb Z/p; \Bbb F_p)\) be pullback of the generator of \(H^2(\Bbb{CP}^\infty)\) under the fibration \(B\Bbb Z/p \to \Bbb{CP}^\infty\) induced from \(S^\infty \to \Bbb{CP}^\infty\) after quotienting by the \(\Bbb Z/p \subset U(1)\) action on the domain; this is simply an isomorphism in even degrees by the discussion above. Then by the fact that \(\beta_p\) is an isomorphism in degree \(1\), we find an element \(x \in H^1(B\Bbb Z/p; \Bbb F_p)\) such that \(\beta_p(x) = y\). By ring structure of the Bockstein, \(\beta(x y^k) = y^{k+1}\) are generators in even degrees, therefore \(xy^k\)’s must generate the odd degrees. This finishes the proof.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, checking that these indeed satisfy the required properties is much harder than it sounds, for full details see Hatcher, Ch 4.L (I might add in more details here as I understand them on the way).</p>

<p>We move on to some computations. To return to the earlier example, observe that for the generator \(\alpha \in H^2(\Bbb{CP}^2; \Bbb F_2)\), \(Sq^2 \alpha = \alpha^2 \neq 0\) and therefore by stabilit we must also have \(Sq^2 \sigma^k(\alpha) \neq 0\), where \(\sigma^k(\alpha) \in H^{2+k}(\Sigma^k \Bbb{CP}^2; \Bbb F_2)\) is the generator of the \(k\)-fold suspension. However, for</p>

\[S^k(S^2 \vee S^4) \simeq S^{2+k} \vee S^{4+k},\]

<p>all Steenrod squares simply vanish, since \(Sq^2\) of a class in \(H^*(S^{2+k})\) stays there by naturality with respect to the retract on that factor, and likewise for the other factor, but there’s no space in the cohomology of spheres for nontrivial cohomology operations. The argument goes through word-by-word with the mapping cone \(C(f)\) in place of \(\Bbb{CP}^2\), where \(f : S^{2n-1} \to S^n\) is a map of Hopf invariant \(1\). This shows the stable stem \(\pi_1^s, \pi_3^s, \pi_7^s\) are all nonzero, as they call contain the stable Hopf fibrations of appropriate degree, which by above are actually non-null.</p>

<p>In fact, one can argue using these Hopf fibrations that \(\pi_2^s, \pi_6^s, \pi_{14}^s\) are nonzero as well: recall that there is a graded ring structure on \(\pi_*^s\) defined upto appropriately stabilizing by \((f, g) \mapsto \Sigma^* f \circ g\), the graded commutativity of this product upto stabilization can be seen by writing the suspension as smashing with the circle many times, and then permuting factors, which tells that the product is homotopic to \(\Sigma^* f \wedge \Sigma^* g\). The claim is that under this product, the squares of the Hopf fibrations are stably nonzero. Suppose \(h : S^{n+1} \to S^n\) is a suspension of the Hopf map, and let \(C_n\) denote the mapping cone. If \(\Sigma h \circ h : S^{n+2} \to S^n\) is nullhomotopic, consider the map \(S^{n+3} = D^{n+2} \cup_{S^{n+1}} D^{n+2} \to C_n\) defined on the equator by sending it to the \(n\)-skeleton by \((\Sigma h) \circ h\), on the top hemisphere by the nullhomotopy of \(\Sigma h \circ h\) and on the bottom hemisphere by \(C(\Sigma h) \circ h\). Attach a \(D^{n+4}\) to \(C_h\) along this map to obtain a cell complex \(X\). Then observe \(Sq^2 : H^n(X; \Bbb F_2) \to H^{n+2}(X; \Bbb F_2)\) is, by naturality applied to inclusion of the \((n+2)\)-skeleton, the same as \(Sq^2 : H^n(C_h; \Bbb F_2) \to H^{n+2}(C_h; \Bbb F_2)\) which is a suspension of the corresponding \(Sq^2\) on the mapping cone of the Hopf map, which is the Hopf invariant, \(1\). Thus,</p>

\[Sq^2 : H^n(X; \Bbb F_2) \to H^{n+2}(X; \Bbb F_2)\]

<p>is an isomorphism. Further, we obtain that \(Sq^2 : H^{n+2}(X; \Bbb F_2) \to H^{n+4}(X; \Bbb F_2)\) is the same, since by naturality applied to the quotient map \(X \to X/S^n\) which is an isomorphism above degree \(n\) by cellular homology, \(Sq^2 : H^{n+2}(C_{\Sigma^2 h}; \Bbb F_2) \to H^{n+4}(C_{\Sigma^2 h}; \Bbb F_2)\), once again an isomorphism. Thierefore \(Sq^2 Sq^2 : H^n \to H^{n+4}\) must be an isomorphism but by Adem relations \(Sq^2 Sq^2 = Sq^3 Sq^1 = 0\) as \(Sq^1 = 0\); there’s no \(H^{n+1}\) for it to be nonzero.</p>

<p>(I will probably fill in something about the relation between Steenrod squares and Stiefel-Whitney classes, an analogous relation between Steenrod powers with Chern classes modulo \(p\) will be used in Seiberg-Witten Theory: Part 2. I might end up doing some exercises from Chapter 4.L and write the interesting solutions here, and there’s plenty of examples in Hatcher in any case. Recommendations on computations are welcome.)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="characteristic-classes" /><category term="stable-homotopy-theory" /><category term="steenrod-squares" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[These are some roughly written notes I am preparing as I study Steenrod operations. I expect nothing new beyond what is in Hatcher Chapter 4.L will be said here, but I will mention other references if I use them. This post is not going to be part of a series, and will instead be updated as I progress and decide to write more.]]></summary></entry></feed>